<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The noble stranger As it was acted at the Private House in Salisbury Court, by her Maiesties Servants. The author, L.S.</title>
            <author>L. S. (Lewis Sharpe), fl. 1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12069</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852437</idno>
  <idno type="VID">17760</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240866165</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 22377</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S117222</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99852437e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1007:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The noble stranger As it was acted at the Private House in Salisbury Court, by her Maiesties Servants. The author, L.S.</title>
                  <author>L. S. (Lewis Sharpe), fl. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I[ohn] O[kes] for Iames Becket, and are to be sold at his shop at the Inner Temple gate, in Fleet-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Lewis Sharpe.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17760:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17760:1"/>
            <p>THE NOBLE Stranger. As it was Acted at the Private House in <hi>Salisbury Court,</hi> by her Maiesties Servants.</p>
            <p>The Author, <hi>L. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hor.</bibl>
               <l>Lenius irritant animos demissa per aures,</l>
               <l>Quàm quae sunt oculis commissa fidelibus—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>I. O.</hi> for <hi>Iames Becket,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop at the Inner Temple gate, in Fleet-streete. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:17760:2"/>
            <head>The Actors Names.</head>
            <list>
               <item>KIng of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Honorio</hi> the Stranger.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fabianus</hi> his Friend.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philomusus</hi> a Noble Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Callidus</hi> an envious Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Moronzo</hi> an ancient Lord, Father to <hi>Clara</hi> and <hi>Marania.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mercutio,</hi> A Poet.</item>
               <item>Two Students of the Law.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plod.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fledwit.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pupillus,</hi> A foolish Gentleman.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Women.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Princesse.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marania.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clara.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lady.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Flavia,</hi> a Wench.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17760:2"/>
            <head>To the Worthy <hi>Knight</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund Williams, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough <hi>Poems</hi> of this Nature have sustain'd such cruell fate, as if the (seeming) <hi>Catoes</hi> of the stage had judg'd the world, grown to a <hi>Plurifie</hi> in <hi>Wit,</hi> and no meanes left to <hi>Cure,</hi> save onely <hi>wounding;</hi> This <hi>Play,</hi> (I dare not say how worthy) was received generally well upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> which begets a <hi>hope,</hi> that having parted with my interest in it to the world, it will not fall under <hi>your</hi> Opinion, whom I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to Elect as <hi>Iudge,</hi> not <hi>Patron:</hi> The latter being growne, by servile imitation to a word of forme descends beneath <hi>your</hi> worth: But by the first, <hi>your</hi> Candid cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure has power to curbe that faction,
<pb facs="tcp:17760:3"/> which swelling to be <hi>Criticall,</hi> extends (like bubbles) to such Ayrie thinnesse, that seeming all, they lose themselves to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. As for the name of <hi>Poet,</hi> it is a stile I never aimed at, (though afarre off I have admired their sacred Raptures) and therefore will not be injurious to <hi>your Expectation,</hi> to bribe <hi>your Acceptance</hi> with promising <hi>Workes</hi> of a higher <hi>strain</hi> hereafter, this being only the <hi>Issue</hi> of some vacant houres, which if <hi>you</hi> vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe at like times to smile on, there ends the ambition of him, who at becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming distance, desires to be knowne</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honourer, <hi>Lewis Sharpe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:17760:3"/>
            <head>To his Friend the Author on his Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, called the <hi>Noble Stranger.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>FRiend, from me thou canst not expect a praise,</l>
            <l>My Muse can give no Cypres nor no Baies:</l>
            <l>She cannot though she would be vile, expresse</l>
            <l>One syllable to make thy merits lesse:</l>
            <l>Nor can she, had she rob'd the fluent store</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Donns</hi> wise Genius, make thy merits more:</l>
            <l>No, 'tis thy owne smooth numbers must preferre</l>
            <l>Thy Stranger to the Globe-like Theatre.</l>
            <l>But yet perhaps some squint-ey'd set will look</l>
            <l>Worse then <hi>Magicians</hi> when they spell the book</l>
            <l>Of exorcisme, yet doe not feare the danger</l>
            <l>Of Critick Readers, since thy <hi>Noble Stranger,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With pleasing strains has smooth'd the rugged Fate</l>
            <l>Of oft cram'd Theatres, and prov'd fortunate:</l>
            <l>Smile at their Frownes, for I dare boldly say,</l>
            <l>Who ere dislikes it cannot mend thy Play.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Woolfall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:17760:4"/>
            <head>Prologue.</head>
            <l>BLest Fate protect me! what a lustre's here?</l>
            <l>How many Starres deck this our little spheare?</l>
            <l>And all predominate, have the influence</l>
            <l>To blast, or cherish, punish, or dispence:</l>
            <l>Your aspects yet are cleare, then joyn in one,</l>
            <l>And prove a happy constellation.</l>
            <l>Our Author does beleeve there will not want</l>
            <l>Some to subscribe the Factious Covenant</l>
            <l>Of your prescitian wits, if such there are,</l>
            <l>Proclaime 'hem Rebells, and bid open warre.</l>
            <l>'Las Poesie's become so shallow now,</l>
            <l>All knowes to judge, what like, what disallow.</l>
            <l>The briske Shops fore-man undertakes with's Ell</l>
            <l>To sound the depth of <hi>Aganippas</hi> Well:</l>
            <l>Weigh out each syllable, measure each line,</l>
            <l>And then with as much confidence define</l>
            <l>Whether false or currant, as those who know</l>
            <l>Distinction 'twixt <hi>Phaebean</hi> straines and low.</l>
            <l>Our Country audience too will crye downe playes;</l>
            <l>And why, there is not foole enough he sayes.</l>
            <l>Gentlemen, y' are grown queasie too of late,</l>
            <l>'Tis meere variety does satiate.</l>
            <l>Faith use our Author well, breath gentle ayre:</l>
            <l>Force not his blooming hopes to a despaire.</l>
            <l>'Tis the first accent of his tender Muse,</l>
            <l>He hopes 'twill please you; if not, doe not use</l>
            <l>A severe Censure, for by me he prayes</l>
            <l>Crowne not with Cypres, though you give no Bayes.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="body_of_play">
            <pb facs="tcp:17760:4"/>
            <head>The Noble Stranger.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACTVS PRIMVS.</head>
               <stage>Senate flourish. Enter King of <hi>Naples,</hi> on his head a wreath of Bayes, as from Conquest, Honorio, Fabianus, Philomusus, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidus, Souldiers and attendants at one side of the Stage: Moron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo, Princesse, Clara, Marania, &amp;c. at the other.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow fares our Princely daughter? how hast thou</l>
                  <l>Brook'd the long absence of our tedious warre,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith we have in blood drown'd those Rebells</l>
                  <l>That sought the downfall of our Peace and State,</l>
                  <l>And now return'd, crown'd with victorious Laurell?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Most royall Father, I have with sighes and teares,</l>
                  <l>Numbred the jarring minutes since your sad</l>
                  <l>Departure, and had ere this been wrapt i'the cold</l>
                  <l>Embraces of the grave, had not the great Antidote</l>
                  <l>Of a Fathers blessing, given me at</l>
                  <l>Your departure, beene my Protector from</l>
                  <l>Death and Fortunes frowne, a renewing of</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:5"/>
                  <l>Which, thus on my knees I crave. <stage>Kneeles.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Rise, thou hast it:</l>
                  <l>And may all those joyes that tender mothers</l>
                  <l>Wish their young infants, playing in their armes,</l>
                  <l>Be multiply'd upon thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>The King's transported.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Has he not cause, possest of such a treasure;</l>
                  <l>That did Kings know it, they would pay their Crownes</l>
                  <l>As tribute to her vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>You speak not as a stranger of the Court;</l>
                  <l>But like one had spent his time in study</l>
                  <l>Of the Courtly Rhetoricke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>No more: see the King addresses him</l>
                  <l>This way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And now the rugged brow of Warre is</l>
                  <l>(By that power which protects Kings sacred persons,</l>
                  <l>And their rights) made faire and smooth agen,</l>
                  <l>Looke with a gracious eye on these whose true</l>
                  <l>Worth deserves the stile of Noble: these</l>
                  <l>Are they whose armes and swords have beene</l>
                  <l>Supporters of our lives and State, so as</l>
                  <l>In honour we must needs shew such grace</l>
                  <l>Their valour has deserv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>All that a maid may doe, ty'd by duty</l>
                  <l>To a Fathers will, freely I performe: <stage>They kisse her hand.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>As for the Common Souldiers, let your</l>
                  <l>Bounty flow in Gold as largies for their</l>
                  <l>Well spent labours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moronzo</hi> 'tis your charge to give each one A free reward.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>I shall my Liege.</l>
                  <l>Souldiers meet me at the publicke Treasury.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                  <l>We shall; Heavens crown our King with peace. <stage>Ex. Sold.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>But for these, my Kingdome's all too little,</l>
                  <l>Especially this Gentleman, being <stage>To Honorie.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>A stranger: and as he sayes a</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sycilian</hi> borne, but for some causes</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:5"/>
                  <l>Recorded within himselfe, which Ile not urge,</l>
                  <l>Came to inhabite in our confines, and</l>
                  <l>When our Quarrell, almost desperate with</l>
                  <l>The enemy had like to be overthrowne</l>
                  <l>For want of present aid, this most noble</l>
                  <l>Deserver of the stile of valour, not</l>
                  <l>Onely in person, but with a flowing</l>
                  <l>Measure of Coyne and Servants came unto</l>
                  <l>Our aide, by which we wonne the day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>The King does largely praise him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>And nobly he deserves it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>We're but foyles to set his lustre off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Envy no honour the King pleases to conferre</l>
                  <l>Upon him: for in his noble breast both</l>
                  <l>Our deservings meet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Not I Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Great King, how ere you please to shoure thus</l>
                  <l>Your favours on my poore deserts, being</l>
                  <l>A stranger, and one that came not to your</l>
                  <l>Aid alone for honour; but incited by heaven,</l>
                  <l>And justice of the cause, which I was bound</l>
                  <l>In duty to performe, being a subject,</l>
                  <l>Though no native, and in that you might</l>
                  <l>Challenge what was done as duty, not thus</l>
                  <l>Descend to give me thankes for that which was</l>
                  <l>Your owne before: For had my starres allotted</l>
                  <l>Me heire to a Kingdome, this bare</l>
                  <l>Acknowledgement had beene more than my</l>
                  <l>Merit could deserve, or state ere recompence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>A Noble gentleman, and seems the throne</l>
                  <l>Of vertue: something within me is not</l>
                  <l>Well; I feele a flame about my heart, which</l>
                  <l>For the present I must suppresse.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Your modesty <hi>(Honorio)</hi> striving</l>
                  <l>To cloud that voluntary aid you gave us,</l>
                  <l>With an impulsive duty, does but</l>
                  <l>(In me) increase your value and lay a</l>
                  <l>Stronger ground for a more firme affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:6"/>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Look this wayes Sir; 'tis these whose true valour,</l>
                  <l>And brave atchievements, merits this flowing</l>
                  <l>Language: for what poore service my ability</l>
                  <l>Coud performe (though 'twas by Heavens all-guiding</l>
                  <l>Power) directed to a good event,</l>
                  <l>Yet came it late: but these, when your enemies</l>
                  <l>Plumes wav'd with triumphant glory on their</l>
                  <l>Helmets top, these flew like lightning, shot</l>
                  <l>From the hand of <hi>Jove,</hi> and blasted those</l>
                  <l>Rebells in their height of glory: but when</l>
                  <l>I came, their bravest forces were decay'd,</l>
                  <l>(Though their number exceeded yours) their</l>
                  <l>Battalias broken, their Ensignes lost, their</l>
                  <l>Leaders slaine, and onely a vast confusion</l>
                  <l>Was their head: there 'twas easie to resist</l>
                  <l>Where order was not guide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I should expresse an ingratitude that</l>
                  <l>Woud for ever blast the name of King,</l>
                  <l>If not render these that honour their</l>
                  <l>Valour has deserv'd: tis true, they fought</l>
                  <l>Bravely, and every stroak, like deaths fatall</l>
                  <l>Sithe, hew'd downe their enemies before 'hem:</l>
                  <l>Yet nere the lesse, we had o'most lost the day,</l>
                  <l>When you like a second <hi>Mars</hi> brake forth, and</l>
                  <l>And gave us victory: their helpes most sweet, prevents</l>
                  <l>The greatest danger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>There's no contending 'gainst your gracious bounty:</l>
                  <l>Shield me Divinity, what feele I here!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>VVell <hi>Fabianus</hi> and <hi>Callidus,</hi> be neere</l>
                  <l>In person as affection to us.</l>
                  <l>And for you <hi>Honorio,</hi> chuse your place:</l>
                  <l>You have such freedome as becomes your worth.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philomusus,</hi> though we have hitherto</l>
                  <l>Beene silent in your praise; we doe confesse</l>
                  <l>How much we owe to your free noble spirit:</l>
                  <l>And though traduc't by such whose contagious</l>
                  <l>Breath will prove their owne bane: tis enough we</l>
                  <l>Know thy worth, that thou canst as well</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:6"/>
                  <l>Court <hi>Bellona</hi> in a shade of horrour,</l>
                  <l>As tread a peacefull measure in a Pallace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>This Character my Liege so farre scapes me,</l>
                  <l>As makes me doubt to whom your intents are Directed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>To thee alone <hi>Philomusus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Say Lords, enjoyes not that man a noble Genius,</l>
                  <l>Who can, and will when warre assaults, lend aid</l>
                  <l>Unto his Soveraigne, and when faire peace</l>
                  <l>Triumphs in height of glory, fill all his</l>
                  <l>Court with pleasure: we have, with no lesse</l>
                  <l>Admiration, beheld the worthy</l>
                  <l>Labours of thy Pen, where every Line</l>
                  <l>Has captivated fancy, then those thy</l>
                  <l>Brave atchievements in the field.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>VVere I not man, this language were enough</l>
                  <l>To staine my cheeks with blushes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon</speaker>
                  <l>Whats he the King pleases so much to honour?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>One whose praise is no Hyperbole to his worth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Well <hi>Philomusus,</hi> you must spurre on your</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pegasus</hi> for some new invention</l>
                  <l>To Crowne our peacefull triumph: to morrow</l>
                  <l>We shall expect a Masque.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>The time is suddaine, you'll</l>
                  <l>Not expect it rare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no: lead on before</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Flourish. Ex. omnes, manet</hi> Philomusus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil</speaker>
                  <l>Tomorrow, 'tis somewhat suddaine,</l>
                  <l>And startles my invention. <stage>Enter <hi>Mercutio.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mercutio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>My honour'd Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art hap'ly met:</l>
                  <l>The King has impos'd somewhat a suddaine</l>
                  <l>Taske on my weake Muse, to prepare a Masque:</l>
                  <l>Thou art a pretty Poet, and maist give me</l>
                  <l>A hint for the device; I have esteemed it</l>
                  <l>One of the defects in Nature to scorne</l>
                  <l>Advise from those whose worth cou'd yield it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:7"/>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Faith my Lord, I have such obligation</l>
                  <l>To your merit, that I shou'd count my best</l>
                  <l>Of labours, crown'd in that act shoud serve you:</l>
                  <l>Yet withall, so much I prize your honour,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd not have you (might I presume to</l>
                  <l>Counsell) draw the same aire with him who is</l>
                  <l>But thought a Poet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>The reason.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>O my Lord, experience produces many:</l>
                  <l>'Twill take off from the glory of your worth,</l>
                  <l>Shou'd you in your workes expresse a soule</l>
                  <l>Active as Celestiall fire, a sence</l>
                  <l>Profound as Oracle; such as wou'd dart</l>
                  <l>Amazement at the world; yet wou'd the</l>
                  <l>Canker <hi>Envy</hi> feed upon your honour,</l>
                  <l>And charge you with such imputations</l>
                  <l>As wou'd transport your soule but to imagine,</l>
                  <l>Much lesse be guilty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>How prethee; with what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>I have, with an inraged spirit, heard</l>
                  <l>The Monster-multitude traduce you, and such</l>
                  <l>Men, whose very hearts wou'd scorne whats not</l>
                  <l>Heroicke, imputing noble actions as vaine-glorious:</l>
                  <l>And when their eyes and eares were witnesse</l>
                  <l>Of your seraphick Contemplations:</l>
                  <l>Glutted with envy wou'd charge you with</l>
                  <l>Keeping stipendary Muses: the like</l>
                  <l>To others, 'cause they inherite more by</l>
                  <l>Nature than learning does bestow, and whose</l>
                  <l>Chaste Virgin Muse, wou'd scorne</l>
                  <l>An adulterate straine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>This all <hi>(Mercutio?)</hi> nay then Ile not doe</l>
                  <l>Them that courtesie to feare, I shou'd</l>
                  <l>Esteeme that glory darker than <hi>Chaos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cou'd from their slight breath admit</l>
                  <l>Privation: no, no, the curse of dulnesse</l>
                  <l>Pursue 'hem all, I am above their spight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:7"/>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>But pray my Lord, where is that exquisite</l>
                  <l>Sprightly wit, you formerly were wont</l>
                  <l>To converse withall, I need not name him,</l>
                  <l>You know him by th' Character.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Very well <hi>Mercutio;</hi> he has</l>
                  <l>Throwne away the Laurell, gain'd ith'</l>
                  <l>Court and City, for a fresher, and one</l>
                  <l>More free from envy in the field.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>His worth deserves it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>No more of this; to the ground of our device;</l>
                  <l>What thinke you of— <stage>Whispers.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pupillus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>This Court is a brave place to live in: oh if I could come to speake, or be acquainted with the Lord <hi>Philomusus,</hi> whom the whole Townes long tongue talkes on for the brave wit; and by miracle prove a wit too; I would paint the great Posts at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers dore, turne Praetor of the City, and keepe open house for all the wits ith' towne; and some of 'hem poore soules have neede on't: for I have heard they are glad oft-times to feede upon stone in a Cathedrall Church— Those were acute wits by my faith law— I am within smell of some Gallants—and sight of 'hem too — Impudence! O impudence! possesse mee — I will speake to hem—Worshipfull Lords— I have an eternall ambition, to salute you in the lower part—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>In the name of innocence—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>No sir, in my owne name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis all one, I doe applaud your sweet humility, Honourable Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Y' are mistaken: I was never so much honoured before: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I meet with some that worships me sometimes, but you may perhaps prophesie, (as the vulgar terme it) in calling me honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable at first sight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Now by <hi>Pernassus,</hi> he resembles bright <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Who I Sir, that were fine yfaith—But harke you a word in your eare, I would bee loath to bewray my selfe before every one—but that <hi>Apollo</hi> was my owne Uncle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Now <hi>Phoebus</hi> he was.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I have sed it Sir—He sold Sun-dialls at the signe of the
<pb facs="tcp:17760:8"/> Bay-tree: oh he was as fine a man by report, as ever told what's a Clocke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>A youth of <hi>Apollo's</hi> race! 'fore <hi>Iove</hi> you must needes be fortunate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope so: to tell you the troth, my Father was a Citizen, and a Mercer, and having a larger fortune upon his head than the rest of his neighbours, met with good pay-masters, and after his Decease my mother wou'd be sure, if any man tooke up her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, he shou'd put in security, which raised her too: but grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old, and finding commings in to be but short, last fall kickt up her heeles, and left me all the wealth she had: Now in good faith Sir, having this estate, I have a great desire to ride in the high way of preferment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>How meane you sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>To be made a Courtier, and a wit—I have money e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and would be loath to have either wit or honour but what be paid for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>He sayes well in that few has.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>But I wou'd faine speake with the Lord <hi>Philomusus,</hi> they say he's able to teach wit, and procure Honour too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Why this is the Lord <hi>Philomusus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou didst ill to discover me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O I beseech your Lordship to pitty my honourable inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the desire I have to be made a Wit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>He might write <hi>nil ultra,</hi> that perform'd it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Here's Gold sir: a soveraigne metall for a wit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I have no need on't, pray keep it sir: how shal's be rid of him?—I have it; <hi>Mercutio</hi> dost heare, thou maist want (the Generall disease of Poets) 'twere justice thou didst pursue this humour both for profit and delight: Ile referre him to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>If you thinke fit, <hi>I</hi> care not to bestow some idle houres on him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe so.—Doe you heare Sir, this Gentleman can performe what you desire better, and with more speed than <hi>I.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Say you so sir: with all my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe: my affaires call me away. Farewell <hi>Mercutio.</hi>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Good day to your Lordship.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> want onely friends and impudence—Now if <hi>I</hi> might
<pb facs="tcp:17760:8"/> be so happy to find both in you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall finde me simply honest.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Of that I make no question: but if you have e're a spare purse of money about you, 'twoud not be cast away, I shall use some in making friends at Court.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe they buy friendship here then you shall have money to pay for't—There Sir. <stage>Gives him money.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>You must have instructions too before you come, how to deport your selfe both in Discourse and manners: my imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are now somewhat weighty in affaires of State; may I but know your lodging, I shall attend you there at some time more opportune both for your selfe and me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>With all my heart: I have committed my selfe to the Inns of Chancery, for the better grace; but feeding ith' Commons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees not with my stomacke; so as I have my dyet in a little Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley hard by at a Cooks house, where you may finde me above the eating houres. You may know the shop by a Calves head com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>I make no question but to finde you there sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Very likely Sir; pray keep your promise. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>I shall not faile. <stage>Enter <hi>Flavia.</hi>
                     </stage> Who's that walkes there so demurely? oh 'tis <hi>Flavia,</hi> the Court Jennet, one that has try'd all constitutions, complexion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, from the Lord under the Canopy to th' Page ith' Lobby, was once an easie doing waiting woman, that wou'd fall in love with this Lords begge, and that Revellers backe, till at last su'd, pray'd, and wonne with oathes, wou'd scarce hold breathing, she grew rotten ripe, and fell with every touch (poxe on't, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber she'd needs trye a Poets straine too) now ith' name of Venery what's she musing on? how to preserve her beauty till the next fall: Ile interrupt her; <hi>Flavia</hi> how is &amp; wench?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Is what sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Is any thing, every thing—What a poxe ail'st? this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour becomes thee scurvily; thou wo't spoyle that little hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somnesse thou hast left. What wouldst thou say wench, if I cou'd helpe thee to a husband, a young husband, a rich husband, one thou mightst Cuckold at his beds feet, and he not a grain the wiser.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:9"/>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>You talke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Talke? by this hand I ne're came short of doing with thee yet, though I paid for't—Come, out of pitty I owe thee a good turne, and if I can, will do't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas Sir, He not marry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Not marry; why what a devill dost thou meane to doe? live to be abhominable ugly, and scorn'd by th' Foote-boyes, goe to Law with Laundresses, for scratching out thy eyes, trust that little stock of money thou hast gathered to set up a house of Garna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ith' Suburbs, with a publicke Notary, he breaks and runnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to <hi>Amsterdam;</hi> live too friend lesse, eye-lesse, toothlesse, and thy Nose notable to endure a jest.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>I must confesse you alleage strong reasons—But pish, thou dost but jest <hi>Marc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then farewell, and a pox take thee at first, for 'twill have thee it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>I th' once; which end?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ith' worst <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> about thee: prethee let a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> goe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Stay, this is but Poeticke rage, a Rapture— Tell me who is't?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou't be mak'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e tell thee: 'Tis a Citizens sonne, one borne by inheritance to be a Cuckold; and thy marrying of him will not crosse his Fate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe you thinke to effect it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh you may worke him like Waxe. <hi>Tom Fled-wit,</hi> and <hi>will Plod</hi> at his fellow Students in the Innes of <hi>Chancery,</hi> they'l doe you any courtesie you knows, If they bee not acquainted with him, they shall; like meet 'hem there tomorrow, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>If it proceed, and take effect, I am all yours. The Court is risen from supper, I must away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord <hi>Philomusus</hi> expects. Me too: Farewell. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Princesse</hi> and <hi>Clara.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>But did my looks betray so strange a Conflict in my heart?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam they did; and one but of a dull discerning eye.
<pb facs="tcp:17760:9"/> Might well perceive those sparkling flames, shot like Comets from your eyes, to speake a stranger fire Had surpriz'd your heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet strove I to suppresse 'hem with all the Rationall powers of my soule, but it Avail'd not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Not to be taxt of flattery, I dare</l>
                  <l>With confidence affirme, if one that's mortall</l>
                  <l>And compos'd of earth, (as he that's greatest</l>
                  <l>Is no more, although compacted of</l>
                  <l>A purer mold) can but deserve a blisse so</l>
                  <l>Great as is your love: <hi>Honorio</hi> is the man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>But prethee lock up ith' privatst concave Of thy breast, the passion I have discover'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile not name it to my selfe, least the aire Convey it to some others eare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>This shall binde</l>
                  <l>Me to thy bosome. <stage>Enter <hi>Honorie</hi> and <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>See <hi>Honorio</hi> and his friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>The Princesse in private conference, Lets withdraw.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee come forward enjoy thy wonted freedome.</l>
                  <l>What Magick spell has charm'd thee into</l>
                  <l>Dulnesse; come, I gesse the cause: flye not that fire,</l>
                  <l>For want of which thou thus becom'st a</l>
                  <l>Frozen Statue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>What starting backe <hi>Fabianus?</hi> doe you</l>
                  <l>Make our presence fearefull to your stranger</l>
                  <l>Friend, one to whom our Country in part does</l>
                  <l>It Freedome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam not I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis well and you con'd possesse me with an</l>
                  <l>Opinion, that he who has out-fac'd</l>
                  <l>An Army, shou'd shrinke at a Ladyes</l>
                  <l>Presence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, impute it not to feare, but a</l>
                  <l>Religious awe, that dares not approach</l>
                  <l>So much Divinity, but with a sacred</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:10"/>
                  <l>Preparation, such as when the holy</l>
                  <l>Priest, bowes at the Altar of incensed</l>
                  <l>Deities.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>So late a Souldier, and so soon a Courtier.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Your softnes Madam, would convert what were Most Barbarous to Civill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>You wou'd make a fine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amorato.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>I shou'd be proud to be what you create mee—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Lady 'thas pleas'd the Princes to entertaine</l>
                  <l>Discourse with my best friend: will you not</l>
                  <l>Taxe me of too great presumption, if I</l>
                  <l>Lay hold on this occasion to present my service.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <p>To love and honour you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>For what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>For your beauty, for those faire eyes that have Transfixt my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, rather hate 'hem, be reveng'd, and wish 'Hem blind as <hi>Cupid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <p>Wish to eclips those heavenly lamps that lend The world their light.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Courtship is too light and ayrie to</l>
                  <l>Obtaine beleefe; this language wou'd doe well</l>
                  <l>To such who love to heare men runne division</l>
                  <l>On their praise: I can heare you as a Courtier,</l>
                  <l>But your speeches will as soone finde death in</l>
                  <l>My forgetfulnesse, as they receiv'd a</l>
                  <l>Superfluous life from your fluent braine—</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Moronzo, Callidus,</hi> and <hi>Marania.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Mischiefe of this prevention; I feare</l>
                  <l>I have too much slighted him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir this Noblenesse becomes you, not to</l>
                  <l>Seeke to surprize a Virgins tender heart,</l>
                  <l>Apt for any impression, before</l>
                  <l>You had gain'd her parents liking and</l>
                  <l>Consent; to which I shall the sooner yield,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:10"/>
                  <l>Having so sure a symptome of your</l>
                  <l>Reall worth; if all men bore your mind,</l>
                  <l>We shou'd not daily view the frequent ruine</l>
                  <l>Of prepostrous matches.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>And sir rest confident in me, I nere will Yield my heart, but where you give my hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <p>May thy duty prove to all a faire example.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I will not urge your hasty answer, though I desire a swift arrivall to my joy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>You say well; things of this nature require</l>
                  <l>Some respite to resolve; we'll chuse some other</l>
                  <l>Time to furnish this discourse—There's the</l>
                  <l>Princesse and your sister; give your attendance,</l>
                  <l>Urgent imployments calls me away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <p>Your humble servant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>Enough, here's Company.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Who are these, <hi>Honorio</hi> and <hi>Fabianus?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My heart swells to behold 'hem; 'twere as</l>
                  <l>Possible a Common-wealth shou'd stand,</l>
                  <l>When there are two Competitors for th'Crowne,</l>
                  <l>As I to brooke their glory that eclipses</l>
                  <l>Mine: Paid not these veines as large</l>
                  <l>A tribute to that Crimson flood as theirs?</l>
                  <l>Honour's as blind as fate, and knowes to</l>
                  <l>Distribute justly: but Ile obscure this passion,</l>
                  <l>Till a just revenge does meet me.</l>
                  <l>Worthy <hi>Honorio.</hi> Noble <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Both yours to serve you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>It growes late, lets to our Chamber.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <p>Lights there for the Princesse. <stage>Ex. omnes, man. <hi>Hon.</hi> &amp; <hi>Fab.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay friend a word, what successe?</l>
                  <l>I perceiv'd the Princesse view'd you</l>
                  <l>With an attractive eye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Didst marke it, and retaine thy former Temper; wer't not Planet-strook with those Starre-like eyes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <p>There was another, though not in so high A Spheare, by whose influence my heart
<pb facs="tcp:17760:11"/> Receiv'd a flame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>I did observe your Complement with <hi>Clara:</hi> Say, dost thou affect her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <p>Deare, as the expectation of my future Blisse.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>O friend thou art happy, there is equality</l>
                  <l>In fortune betwixt you two: but what alas</l>
                  <l>Remaines for me that am a stranger, and</l>
                  <l>A Subject, one she knowes not whence</l>
                  <l>Deriv'd; his being onely to passe by her with</l>
                  <l>A silent admiration, till my owne flames</l>
                  <l>Consume me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, lets recollect the ornaments of</l>
                  <l>Man, our reason, and enjoy the treasure</l>
                  <l>Of our friendship in a timely Councell,</l>
                  <l>— What fittest course to steere:</l>
                  <l>Lets to our Chamber, and discourse it there.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACTƲS SECƲNDƲS.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Honorio,</hi> and a Boy.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>SEE <hi>Aurora</hi> puts on her Crimson blush,</l>
                  <l>And with resplendant raies guilds o're the top</l>
                  <l>Of you aspiring hill: the pearly dew</l>
                  <l>Hangs on the Rose buds top, and knowing it</l>
                  <l>Must be anon exhaled, for sorrow shrinkes</l>
                  <l>It selfe into a teare: the early Larke,</l>
                  <l>With other winged Choristers of the Morne,</l>
                  <l>Chanting their Anthems in harmonious aires:</l>
                  <l>Let those whose sleepes are sound, and quiet as</l>
                  <l>The dead of night, rise and partake those sweets</l>
                  <l>This place affords, they are not for me to joy in.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:11"/>
                  <l>These are the Princesse lodgings,</l>
                  <l>That her window! Come boy, breath</l>
                  <l>Out my sorrowes in a mournfull aire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <stage>Song.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>TEll me <hi>Jove,</hi> should she disdaine,</l>
                     <l>Whether were it greater paine,</l>
                     <l>Silent in thy flames to dye,</l>
                     <l>Or say I love, and she deny.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Flames supprest, doe higher grow,</l>
                     <l>Shou'd she scorne when she does know</l>
                     <l>Thy affection; thou shalt prove</l>
                     <l>A glorious Martyrdome for love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Better to Loves mercy bow,</l>
                     <l>She may burne as well as thou:</l>
                     <l>On then tim'rous heart proceed:</l>
                     <l>For wounds are death that inward bleed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Princesse</hi> above.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>What Harmon is that? say who's below?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>The admirer of your vertues Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Who, <hi>Honorio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>The same.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Was it you that sent those pleasant accents to me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>My duty made me strive to be the first</l>
                  <l>This morning might salute your care.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>I shall find a time for recompence:</l>
                  <l>'Tis a pleasant walk you tread,</l>
                  <l>Keep on your path.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Your humble Honourer; oh love be now</l>
                  <l>Propitious, and flatter not my poore</l>
                  <l>Credulous heart, with a gentle gale of</l>
                  <l>Comfort, and suffer't to split against</l>
                  <l>The Rocks of ruine; no, thy heart I know</l>
                  <l>Is tender as thy youth, and does relent</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:12"/>
                  <l>To know my sufferings.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>My friend, I am too narrow to containe</l>
                  <l>My joy, thou'rt happily arriv'd to beare</l>
                  <l>A part; I have seene the Princesse.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <p>Is her highnesse so early stirring?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes <hi>Fabianus,</hi> and my heart that now</l>
                  <l>Felt heavier to me than an <hi>Atlas</hi> load</l>
                  <l>Shee ha's rarifi'd to ayre.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Princesse</hi> and <hi>Clara.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <p>See she's descended, with her the Mistris Of my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus have I seene the dawning day break from The Easterne hills.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>Morrow <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Your creature Madam: Lady vouchsafe your lip, <stage>To <hi>Clara</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>With the Exchange of some few words in private.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>You keep still your constant walke <hi>Honorio:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Twas a pleasing ayre you last presented;</l>
                  <l>Me thought it bare a sound of Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, be pleased to give it some other</l>
                  <l>Stile; for me to sound unto your care that name</l>
                  <l>Were a presumption farre above his, that</l>
                  <l>Stole the fire from Heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>You seeme modest, to encrease your value:</l>
                  <l>Come I know you are in love, who is't</l>
                  <l>You serve?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, beleeve my tongue was never</l>
                  <l>Stranger to my heart; at every looke you</l>
                  <l>Doe create new flames; and like the vestall</l>
                  <l>Hearth, which once extinguisht, nought</l>
                  <l>Cou'd replenish, except like Holy fire</l>
                  <l>Your eyes does wound my heart, and with a smile</l>
                  <l>You cure againe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Courtiers are so prone, on each slight fancy</l>
                  <l>Of a Ladyes humour, to beleeve themselves</l>
                  <l>The onely object of their loves, that we,</l>
                  <l>Nor know how to give look or smile, but straight</l>
                  <l>With flattering Oratory they lay traines</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:12"/>
                  <l>To blow up our unspotted honours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>O harbour not a thought so wicked of</l>
                  <l>My love, lest the entertainment (being</l>
                  <l>Wrongfully suppos'd) staine the immaculate</l>
                  <l>Purity of your soule.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you heare not me accuse you, but in</l>
                  <l>An affaire so important as is the cause</l>
                  <l>Of love, she that doubts not, shall nere attaine</l>
                  <l>To surety.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon, Madam, if with unhallowed breath</l>
                  <l>I sound what may prove offensive to your eare,</l>
                  <l>Blame not my forward zeale, you being</l>
                  <l>The Motive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>On then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>I love you Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Again I breath my soule—I love you Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Twas boldly utter'd, what prompts you to this Insolence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh love, I'me blasted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>The Princesse seems mov'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>But a storm, 'twill soone be over.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you, because a stranger, ignorant</l>
                  <l>Of our Lawes, which makes it death for any man</l>
                  <l>To move affection to her, who is</l>
                  <l>Heire to th'Crowne? if so, you may plead excuse:</l>
                  <l>Else know you are guilty of a Crime, will pluck</l>
                  <l>The Lawes severity on your head.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Can Law or torture fright his soule, who is</l>
                  <l>Every houre extended on the wrack;</l>
                  <l>No, since you despise me, 'twill adde unto</l>
                  <l>My future happinesse, when Love shall know</l>
                  <l>I'me one that dy'd your Martyr, and for my</l>
                  <l>Body, when entomb'd in earth, a <hi>Cypres</hi> Tree</l>
                  <l>Shall spring up from my grave, under whose shade</l>
                  <l>Such mournfull lovers, as are punish'd</l>
                  <l>With disdaine, shall come and pay sad tribute</l>
                  <l>Of their teares, which by that charitable</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:13"/>
                  <l>Aire converts; the falling dew into a frost,</l>
                  <l>Shall be congeal'd, and raise to my sad</l>
                  <l>Memory a lasting Monument of</l>
                  <l>Transparent Christall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay cleare your brow, I' me none of those that take</l>
                  <l>Pleasure in tormenting Lovers: 'twere a</l>
                  <l>Sinne the gods themselves wou'd punish, shou'd my</l>
                  <l>Disdaine raze so faire a building; retaine</l>
                  <l>Your manly freedome, although I know it</l>
                  <l>Sutes not with my birth to give incouragement</l>
                  <l>To a Subjects love, yet we're bound to</l>
                  <l>Cherish true worth, though in persons</l>
                  <l>Of a meaner ranke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh let me adore the miracle of Nature;</l>
                  <l>You speak a soule more perfect than an Angels.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Cease these hyperboles, and rest assured,</l>
                  <l>As time shall increase my opinion of</l>
                  <l>Your worth, I shall dispose my heart—</l>
                  <l>But secresie as you expect my love,</l>
                  <l>Or your own safety—so—farewell: Come <hi>Clara,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Father expects us at the Temple—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot stay sir; but in that ring receive</l>
                  <l>Your answer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>I accept it as a sentence of despaire or blisse:</l>
                  <l>—See friend</l>
                  <l>What happinesse is here contain'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Hast prevail'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and if thy love prospers as mine has done,</l>
                  <l>We'l both sing hymnes to <hi>Cythereas</hi> Son. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Callidus</hi> and <hi>Marania.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Lady, your Fathers goodnesse has left you</l>
                  <l>To your owne dispose; and I, the admirer</l>
                  <l>Of your vertues, have free leave to present</l>
                  <l>My best affection; then save that creature,</l>
                  <l>Whose life depends on you, whose every</l>
                  <l>Power ownes not himselfe, but you:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:13"/>
                  <l>You are that Deity, to whom my heart</l>
                  <l>Presents its first devotion, and in</l>
                  <l>A holy flame remains a sacrifice, till</l>
                  <l>You please accept it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>I shou'd prove unto my selfe unjust,</l>
                  <l>In the neglect of one that nobly loves:</l>
                  <l>Therefore what affection I may bestow,</l>
                  <l>And yet retaine my freedome, I meane</l>
                  <l>That freedome, by which I may on just occasion</l>
                  <l>Withdraw my heart; I were ingratefull</l>
                  <l>Shou'd I not present.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>May I become the scorne of time, and all</l>
                  <l>Mens hate pursue me, when I prove so foule</l>
                  <l>To give occasion you call back your love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Cease these hasty protestations, and</l>
                  <l>I assure my selfe the purenesse of your soule</l>
                  <l>Is without spot or blemish; and while you</l>
                  <l>So continue, I shall boast me happy ith'</l>
                  <l>Glory of such a choise.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>O let me flye into your bosome, and</l>
                  <l>On your lip confirme my happinesse, there</l>
                  <l>Study some new way of number to multiply</l>
                  <l>My blisse—the treasuries of grace and nature,</l>
                  <l>Were quite exhausted to accomplish your</l>
                  <l>Perfections.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Fie, fie, leave for shame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>What?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>This superfluous language; I am none</l>
                  <l>Of those Ladies that are taken with</l>
                  <l>Poetick Raptures, verses of their haire,</l>
                  <l>Flattering Acrosticks, and their names</l>
                  <l>So dis-joynted with an Anagram, 'twould</l>
                  <l>Puzzle ten Magicians to put 'hem together</l>
                  <l>Againe: I esteeme not golden language;</l>
                  <l>'Twas seldome bestow'd on man, but to</l>
                  <l>Guild a Copper soule within him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you be so cruell to deeme my</l>
                  <l>Language feign'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:14"/>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor am I:</l>
                  <l>I grant you love and Poesie are divine,</l>
                  <l>Commonly infus'd together, yet</l>
                  <l>Ordinarily 'tis ty'd to rules of flattery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Farre be it from me to speak a language</l>
                  <l>Shou'd displease your eare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, more Oratory would but bring</l>
                  <l>The rest into suspition, whether it</l>
                  <l>Be reall, let it suffice, I love you,</l>
                  <l>And if all occurrents sute my expectation,</l>
                  <l>'T shall not be long 'fore <hi>Hymen</hi> scale</l>
                  <l>The Contract</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Heeres the Courts Quotidian,</l>
                  <l>Shakes all about him.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Princesse,</hi> and <hi>Clara; Hon.</hi> and <hi>Fab.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marania,</hi> why had we not your attendance</l>
                  <l>To th' Temple? I gesse the cause.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas my happinesse, with her Fathers leave</l>
                  <l>To hold a short discourse: I hope it does</l>
                  <l>Not offend you Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>By no means: and if it were of love you</l>
                  <l>Treated, may you prosper as I wish my owne desires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>You're bounteous Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Noble <hi>Philomusus,</hi>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Philomusus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Fathers Court is happy in one so</l>
                  <l>Much deserving</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>You too much honour me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>I wou'd have you <hi>Fabianus</hi> and this</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Noble Stranger</hi> mutually friends,</l>
                  <l>Your deserts are so much equall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>I'me left out then:</l>
                  <l>There may be a time for a revenge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets embrace, and prove the <hi>Trium-viri</hi> of</l>
                  <l>True friendship, happy in this union:</l>
                  <l>More happy in that you have</l>
                  <l>Pleas'd to joyne us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Me thinks <hi>Honorio</hi> and the Princesse are</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:14"/>
                  <l>In deepe discourse—</l>
                  <l>Shee smiles in his face—</l>
                  <l>Darts amorous glances—if she shou'd affect</l>
                  <l>Him now; I'de wish no deeper Precipice</l>
                  <l>To his ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the Masquers within are ready.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Then lets away. <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Mercutio, Plod,</hi> and <hi>Fled-wit.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>My sublime Mercurian I by all the Codexes of the Law, thou art the <hi>Primum mobile</hi> of Fancy: If this gull continue but his state of innocence, we shall have Dinners, Sack, and wenches in the Seraglios <hi>gratis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, and we can marry him to <hi>Flavia,</hi> weele drink, dance, and revell with his wife till midnight, and make him carry the Lanthorne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ee heare then, be advis'd by me, you two shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with slight arguments to disswade him from the Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> worke him more into the opinion of your friendship: the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> present the match, be you sure to give fire, and wee shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> up I warrant you Lads.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>Oracle! as I live Oracle: O I cou'd hugge thee for this, my joviall Juvinell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Then be you sure, when J name the party, to seeme to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll her vertue, beauty, riches, and so forth. And sweare you know her all over to a hair— which you may both with a safe Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, for matter of Knowledge, one oath wou'd serve us, and forty more. <stage>Enter <hi>Pupillus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>See he comes, 'fore <hi>Iove,</hi> feeling for money already — Walke off a little —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Right worthy Sir, may these ten Angells guard you: Oh Celestiall pocket.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Noble and right generous sir, I doe receive 'hem with as much zeale as a Puritan wou'd cheat his father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>And when, and when shall I be indoctrinated, as they say, in these rules of wit and Courtship?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Why when you will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:15"/>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Master <hi>Pupillus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Whoop sir, are you here? who! and you too? and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this Gentleman?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>All of a Messe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>But hark you sir, one word with you: wil you leave the lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, credible, profitable practice of the Law, to study wit and Courtship?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes indeed will I: Doe you thinke I will bee troubled with your Burgage, Sockage, and <hi>Feodum simplex;</hi> your French and Latine, more barbarous than beggers Canting: and for a <hi>Littleton,</hi> 'tis more hatefull to me than a Prayer Booke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Troth Master <hi>Fled-wit</hi> I know not what to say, but <hi>bona fide,</hi> he is one <hi>non compos mentis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>In-law I am of your opinion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>So am not I, I commend him for't. Wou'd you have him sit wearing out his Buttons, 'gainst his Inke-besquirted Desk, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of circumcised Latine in Characters, more antique than Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Hieroglyphicks, transcribing presidents out of old sheep-skins recorded in <hi>Anno Sexcentesimo quarto,</hi> till his head and Braines be as drye and hollow as his pumice-stone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, they shall ne're bring me to it: what though my Father was a Citizen, and a Mercer, yet my mother was a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman borne, and who knowes but shee might have a friend at Court like other Citizens wives, to bring their husbands custome, and them trading: if so, there may be good reason, why I have this Courtly itch upon me: Besides, I'me not the first whose' Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has measured Ladies commodities by th' yard; and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Coach and sixe horses as well as the best o'm.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>So farre <hi>concordat cum recordo,</hi> (as a man may say) and perhaps his Father being a landed man, some Courtier was Tenant in Taile with his Mother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>Very likely: but faith Master <hi>Pupillus,</hi> I cou'd wish you wou'd not leave us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell you I wou'd not be troubled with your Conjuring termes of Law, for the profit you get in ten <hi>Michaelmas</hi> tearms, when your Gownes and Consciences are soyld and dabled alike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Believe it sir, were you not our friend, we wou'd not brook this <hi>Scandalum Magnatum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay be not angry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>Not we sir; because we know every man was not borne
<pb facs="tcp:17760:15"/> with wit enough to be a Lawyer, but for a gallant of these times, the lesse he has the more in fashion. But what will you doe at Court? 'tis not your five hundred a yeare will maintaine your Masques, Playes, Revells, Races, Tennis, Cards, and In, and In with the Ladies, besides your leash of wenches at livery, and when all's brought to a devastation, what then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Tis but trading with some Merchants wife when her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's gone to Sea, to trafficke for Unicornes horne, and I shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want money to bear me standing: 'tis common amongst your broken Cavalleers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>He sayes right, there was one Master <hi>Had-land,</hi> a decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gallant, that had spent all his meanes in those wayes you have nam'd, and having nothing left, but the remembrance of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer glory, strook in with one Mistris <hi>Sweet-lips</hi> a Com-fit makers wife, and she maintaines him now as bravely as any gallant that weares his sword ith' defence of his back-side.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>This was strange.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Phew—talke of want and be a wit—I'me asham'd on you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, doe but view this gentlemans Physiognomie, does not he looke like one that would be fortunate, or crosse the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe? does not this beard grow in forme of a Senators? Perhaps you'l say he has not that accomplisht wit, learning, or other deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving parts. Why tis ten to one he is the sooner preferred; no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for desert, that rises leisurely and by degrees, honour preferres head-long those that have not too much wit to hinder it: Why I have knowne a gentleman turne away his man, because hee had more wit than himselfe. Then to see what waies there are by mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: a Lady of my acquaintance cast away foure or five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pound upon a paire of Capering Legges, and a Head of Haire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I have a head of haire, and my owne too could caper for a need: Oh that I cou'd thrust my selfe into a Lady of such a Fortune.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>I can assure you sir, there are stranger fortunes fall upon some mens heads.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray don't you thinke, I have a head able to bear as large a Fortune as another man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:16"/>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>A brow for the purpose: I can tell you sir, there is a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy I cou'd name, a handsome Lady, has somewhat more than every one knowes on—</p>
                  <p>You know her Gentlemen— in some part.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>O shee has an estate of twenty Aldermen, besides Frank-tenement Copy-hold, and Tenure in Taile in aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>She's of so gentle a nature too, and so drawing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O delicate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>I protest Sir, if you can but get to bee acquainted with her, you may write your selfe the happiest man alive.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>When may I see her? I long to be at her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Even when you will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>But what shall I doe; I want hard words to Court her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Me.</speaker>
                  <p>How let me see—'tis no matter, Ile tell you, You have read <hi>Littleton,</hi> and the termes of Law.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I ne're read any thing else.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Then you shall Court this Lady ith' Lawyers Dialect, tis new; and cannot but be gratefull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not care for this <hi>Littleton,</hi> and the termes of Law; but if I come to't once, have at her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>First lets to the Taverne and drinke Sack, To whet our wits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Content, a match.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Come Noble Academians, lusty Wine Shall make's immortall, there's our Magazine. <stage>Exeunt omn.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:17760:16"/>
               <head>ACTƲS TERTIƲS.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Callidus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>MAn, in perfection of his primitive purenesse,</l>
                  <l>Was by the gods created just and free:</l>
                  <l>But forfeiting the Charter of those brave</l>
                  <l>Immunities heavens bounty had conferr'd</l>
                  <l>Upon him, in just revenge of his too</l>
                  <l>Wilfull errour, severall passions straight</l>
                  <l>Sprung up to force him hold a conflict</l>
                  <l>In his soule; th'effects of which innated</l>
                  <l>Frailty make me prone, <hi>Honorio,</hi> there;</l>
                  <l>I there's the Kingdomes generall Earth-quake:</l>
                  <l>No honours, titles, favours, but are confer'd</l>
                  <l>On him, when every act of mine might claime</l>
                  <l>A Pyramide; and in honour to brook arrivall</l>
                  <l>Wou'd force antipathy in what were perfect</l>
                  <l>Union: what wou'd not Justice in such a</l>
                  <l>Cause permit? 'twou'd make man conscious of,</l>
                  <l>And act that otherwise might blemish his</l>
                  <l>Creation to performe: I have perceiv'd some</l>
                  <l>Signes of love betwixt <hi>Honorio</hi> and the</l>
                  <l>Princesse; if I can prove it true, it will</l>
                  <l>Be no base revenge to tell the King, since</l>
                  <l>Custome and the Kingdoms Law stiles such</l>
                  <l>Presumption treason; I am resolv'd, I over.</l>
                  <l>Heard them in the presence appoynt to walke</l>
                  <l>Here in the garden: now in yon thicket</l>
                  <l>Ile stay, to heare what language passes</l>
                  <l>Betwixt 'hem: if't be of love, as I doe</l>
                  <l>Presuppose, my just revenge proves duty <stage>Exit behind the Arras.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>To my King: I heare 'hem comming, I must obscure</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:17"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Honorio <hi>and the Princesse.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>You're a Lady in whom consist all that</l>
                  <l>Heaven has rais'd to a perfection:</l>
                  <l>I am too poore to enjoy so great a treasure,</l>
                  <l>And shall be ever, till I grow immortall:</l>
                  <l>Which alone rests in your power to make me:</l>
                  <l>Tis not your birth or fortune that I court,</l>
                  <l>Heaven's witnesse with me: for had you bin an</l>
                  <l>Humble shepherdesse, and I a Monarch,</l>
                  <l>This love had beene, 'cause 'twas decree'd by Fate:</l>
                  <l>When I first saw you, me thought my soule was</l>
                  <l>Forc'd to obey a traunce, and as a vision</l>
                  <l>My amazed sight beheld you, the</l>
                  <l>Revolution of those Starre-like eyes deserves</l>
                  <l>A new Astronomy to contemplate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>It sutes my wish, doe doe, bite on, and</l>
                  <l>Swallow thine owne Confusion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorio,</hi> I have heard you, and as</l>
                  <l>A lover allow of this discourse: but do</l>
                  <l>Not too soone betray your selfe to misery:</l>
                  <l>Alas ther's danger in affecting me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not that thing cald danger can affright</l>
                  <l>My soule, were you round inclos'd with</l>
                  <l>Rocks of Marble, whose lofty tops shou'd know</l>
                  <l>No distance 'twixt the skies and them;</l>
                  <l>I wou'd with winged speed scale those</l>
                  <l>Aspiring walls, and in despight of all that</l>
                  <l>Durst detaine you, beare you in my armes</l>
                  <l>Beyond the reach of danger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>So insolent! there may be wayes to curb you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>This does expresse your will, not power, to</l>
                  <l>Attaine our safety, if you proceed: faith</l>
                  <l>Therefore leave to love me, 'twill prove</l>
                  <l>But the ruine of a worthy man, if e're</l>
                  <l>It come to light—my poore heart is forc't</l>
                  <l>To plead against it selfe—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:17"/>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Who shou'd reveale it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>He does not think an eccho is so neare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Ther's none besides our selves that know it, and <hi>Fabianus</hi> in whom I durst repose my life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay, who's this?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>None but my friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, pardon my suddaine rudenesse; 'tis</l>
                  <l>My love to him, and duty towards you,</l>
                  <l>That prompts me to it: the King, with</l>
                  <l>Rest oth' Lords, are making this way, which</l>
                  <l>Hastned me hither, where I suppos'd you were.</l>
                  <l>To give you notice to breake off discourse,</l>
                  <l>And hast away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy true friendship deserves a Noble</l>
                  <l>Recompence: our next meeting shall be</l>
                  <l>This evening in the private Garden:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>I shall not faile: lets haste away. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>King, Philomusus, Callidus, Moronzo,</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>By the faith I owe to Honour, <hi>Philomusus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Masque was well perform'd upon so short</l>
                  <l>A warning—where's <hi>Honorio,</hi> our but</l>
                  <l>Divided selfe, partner in heart and</l>
                  <l>Kingdome.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Honorio</hi> and <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>He's here my Liege.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorio, Fabianus, Philomusus,</hi> three Jems</l>
                  <l>Make up the poynt verticall in my Laurell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>I serve for nothing: then oh my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>You so much honour us, you make our plenty</l>
                  <l>Poore; rich onely in the amazement of</l>
                  <l>Your bounty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>My Liege, not presuming on my owne</l>
                  <l>Deserts, but your free Justice to revenge</l>
                  <l>The wrong'd, I'me bold to preferre a sute.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou canst aske but what will prove</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:18"/>
                  <l>Our honour to bestow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, my Liege, I have no Monopoly</l>
                  <l>On foot, to draw on my head the curse</l>
                  <l>Of crying misery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I'me confident.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Then thus my Liege, the late grudge betwixt</l>
                  <l>The ancient King of <hi>Portingall,</hi> and your selfe,</l>
                  <l>Sprung from the disappoyntment of the</l>
                  <l>Match, betweene your sister (now Dutches</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Pavia</hi>) and him, by reason of her youth</l>
                  <l>And beauty, not fit for cold embraces:</l>
                  <l>And having made you his proclaimed</l>
                  <l>Enemy (though in your goodnesse you have</l>
                  <l>Never sought to disturbe the quiet of</l>
                  <l>His peace) yet by this meanes many of your</l>
                  <l>Painfull loyall Subjects have sustain'd</l>
                  <l>Great losses on the Seas, by divers ships</l>
                  <l>Belonging to the King of <hi>Portingall;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Amongst which, certaine Merchants, almost</l>
                  <l>Ruin'd in their estate and fortunes, this</l>
                  <l>Morning desir'd me to move your Majesty</l>
                  <l>To grant 'hem Letters of Mart, for taking,</l>
                  <l>In recompence of their losses, such ships</l>
                  <l>Of the adverse party, as their labours and</l>
                  <l>Good successe, may make them owners of.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>The Motion's just and noble, and for thy love</l>
                  <l>To th' right of innocence, we here create</l>
                  <l>Thee Secretary of State, draw what thou thinkst</l>
                  <l>Is fit, our royall Hand and Signet shall</l>
                  <l>Confirme it: and because <hi>Honorio,</hi> and <hi>Fabianus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall grow in honour, as in friendship with you,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorio</hi> we make our Lord high Martiall;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fabianus</hi> publicke Treasurer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>And me not spoken of: I laugh to think</l>
                  <l>How soone their glory will be Eclips'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Onely the contemplation of your bounty</l>
                  <l>Must prove our gratitude.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Enough—Lead on. <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:17760:18"/>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Mercutio</hi> and <hi>Flavia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Was he so taken, and eager at the report?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>As an Usurer of a Prodigall at one and twenty; All fire; if thy practis'd iniquity will but suffer thee to dissemble modesty, thou art as sure of him as the Devill of a Catchpole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>You a wit, and question a womans dissimulation; there's ne're a head ith' City so hard but knowes it by experience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Got to then; doe not you seeme too suddainly won, but hold off with an attractive distance: 'twill make his blood runne hot and higher.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Goe teach a common Gamster to cheat, a Puritane to lye, or a Scrivener to keepe his eares, J neede not your learned Maximes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>But harke you, harke you, a word by th' way: if after all my paines, care, and counsell, you shou'd, like an old Hospitall, forget your founder; play the Gypsie and turne honest forsooth, or thrifty, it shou'd be the last charitable act J'de doe for the whole Sexe on you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Condemne me never to know man more if J doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Goe thy wayes, 'tis a strong oath, and J beleeve thee— J have left <hi>Pupillus,</hi> with his two legall associates, following in a young Practizers pace to th' Hall ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ling the Country, Clyents Block-heads together, till their braines bee as light as the cause some of hem goes to Law for—Body o'ne wench J heare 'hem comming—On with your vizard of vertue now, and dissemble me like a holy sister of the loving Family.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pupillus, Plod,</hi> and <hi>Fled-wit.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>See sir, there is the Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O admirable blacke beauty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>And your noble friend pleading for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam here is the gentleman J so much Commended; and though J say it before his face, He is one of a noble disposition, birth, and fortune.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>He sayes very true Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>Beauteous Madam, pray honour me to kisse your hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Though last in Ceremony, J shou'd be proud To be the first might serve you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:19"/>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Poxe on't, what a block-head was I, I cou'd not say so my selfe—O 'tis a melting Creature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>So sir, we have made the way for you, enter now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>I, I, I cou'd enter, and runne through her too: But what to say when I come at her, I know not—</l>
                  <l>But I will speak to her, and because she shall</l>
                  <l>Not say I speak without book, this learned</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Littleton</hi> shall be my prompter— <stage>Takes out a booke and holds it in his hand, and looks on it at the breaches.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bright, bright Moon-shine of beauty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <l>And why not as well Sun-shine?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh I should come too hot upon her.</l>
                  <l>— <hi>Moderata Misericordia,</hi> Lady.</l>
                  <l>Love like a little theefe has committed Burglary</l>
                  <l>On my heart, rais'd the towne of my Sences.</l>
                  <l>And forces me with hue and cry to your Ladiship.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I have compassion on your flames.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh madam, madam, the best part about me's burnt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>How!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>My heart I meane, and since my eares were</l>
                  <l>Long enough to reach the report of your beauty,</l>
                  <l>I have still desir'd—<hi>Licentiam interloquendi</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With your Ladyship.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>J marry sir, this is somewhat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, when J am once in I can tickle her yfaith.</l>
                  <l>You shall heare me rime too,</l>
                  <l>This Yeare in which love did my heart into his—</l>
                  <l>Balliwicke bring: Is just by computation</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tricesimo</hi> of the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla</speaker>
                  <l>Beleeve it sir, youle put me downe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis my desire Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>You speake in so quaint a Dialect, J understand you not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Hist friend, what does she meane by Dialect?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>A delicate way of speaking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, oh, J beseech you Madam let me be a remitter in</l>
                  <l>Your Grace.—J have chose an action to content you</l>
                  <l>Besides land of all the Tenures in <hi>Littleton:</hi> as</l>
                  <l>Burgage, Sockage, Escuage, Vilienage and Capite,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:19"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cum multis alijs quae nunc praescribere longum est.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Mr. <hi>Pupillus,</hi> I never knew you were a Scholler before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith no great Scholler neither, 'twas all the fruit of ten yeares going to Schoole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Marry enough to make a Divine in some Countries,</l>
                  <l>Where degrees of Schoole are vendable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Why sir, my father was told by a cunning woman, that I should never learne beyond, <hi>As in praesenti,</hi> and so J never strove to go further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Then the Asse: 'twas well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, my heart does make continuall claime to your love, and hopes we shall be joyntenants in affection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you might call my modesty in question,</l>
                  <l>To yield my heart at first to one I never saw before.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Woud you chuse a man by th'fore part Lady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>You wound my intention, sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>And you wound my heart:</l>
                  <l>There's thrust for thrust.</l>
                  <l>But if your coynesse shoud make me prove <hi>Felon de se,</hi> and kil my selfe, you woud be sorry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>I shoud—but pray sir excuse me, at this time</l>
                  <l>To hold longer discourse with you, some serious</l>
                  <l>Affaires urges my departure—farwell noble Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>But one kisse first, and all this gold to buy you Taffata for blacke patches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile not refuse, least you might thinke I scorne.— good day to all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Your servants Lady—we'le come and share.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Do so. <stage>Exit Favia.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iack, Tom,</hi> a word—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh love! love! that makes a man a Skelleton:</l>
                  <l>Let her in part feele the pricke, as well as I,</l>
                  <l>Of thy inflaming Dart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>What thinke you on't?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <l>Beyond thought!</l>
                  <l>Most excellent!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>How ist Sir? beare up.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:20"/>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>I, I, but oh this Lady, this Lady—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Troth Gentlemen this Lady is not so taken with him as we thought, and expected; what think you if—but I wou'd bee loath to speak except I thought he wou'd do't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh any thing gentlemen, any thing—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then what think you if he were inspired?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>How! inspired? that's very fine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>But you know the wayes, and Ceremonies, are Very chargeable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <l>O infinite!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>I care not what it cost, let it be done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Then it shall sir; come, as we goe we will</l>
                  <l>Discourse of it at large, and to morrow</l>
                  <l>It shall be perform'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I be inspir'd? oh fortunate acquaintance. <stage>Ex. omn.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Callidus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy life the forfeit if it prove untrue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>I wish my losse of breath might prove it false:</l>
                  <l>But 'tis a truth as reall, as is the</l>
                  <l>Justice of the gods severe: and I may</l>
                  <l>Safely say, I live preserver of my</l>
                  <l>Countries fame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>O yee gods, why were Kings made the emblemes</l>
                  <l>Of your power, when like poore slaves, we're</l>
                  <l>Subject to the change of various and</l>
                  <l>Inconstant Fortune; have you snatcht up</l>
                  <l>Goodnesse from the earth, and left nought to</l>
                  <l>Inhabit in the breasts of men, but vile</l>
                  <l>Dissimulation, poyson to friendship,</l>
                  <l>And the staine to honour; in whom</l>
                  <l>Shall meaner men dare ever to confide,</l>
                  <l>When Kings themselves rest ignorant</l>
                  <l>Where to trust.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, that treachery shou'd inhabit there</l>
                  <l>Where all men thought Vertue had rais'd her</l>
                  <l>Mansion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:20"/>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>True; I did beleeve <hi>Honorio</hi> to be</l>
                  <l>A man that sooner would have yielded up</l>
                  <l>His heart a prey to Vultures, than to a</l>
                  <l>Thought disloyall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>My Liege, I can informe</l>
                  <l>You more: <hi>Fabianus</hi> is their agent,</l>
                  <l>In this loves affaire: and at that time</l>
                  <l>When your Majesty miss'd <hi>Honorio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He came and gave him private notice to</l>
                  <l>Prevent discovery: this I both saw and heard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>He false too? Hells furies take</l>
                  <l>And confound 'hem all. Will not the whole</l>
                  <l>World, when they shall heare my daughter</l>
                  <l>Stoops to a base affection, laugh, and scorne</l>
                  <l>My vile degenerate issue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>This rage seems Kingly in you: cherish it my Liege.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>They all shall perish if thou prove this true:</l>
                  <l>But if false, and that of spight thou hast</l>
                  <l>Rais'd this vile aspersion, expect a death</l>
                  <l>So horrid, hell shall startle but to heare it nam'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>And 'twere my just desert, if J shou'd live the</l>
                  <l>Staine of innocence: No my gracious</l>
                  <l>Liege, if on your Royall word you'll promise</l>
                  <l>Not discover 'twas J that gave you notice,</l>
                  <l>Cause 'tmay be a Barre betwixt my love</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marania,</hi> and me, whose sister J have</l>
                  <l>Heard affects <hi>Fabianus,</hi> J shall discover</l>
                  <l>The time and place when and where they meet,</l>
                  <l>Then shall your eye and eare be witnesse of my truth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Upon the honour of a King, Jle not disclose</l>
                  <l>A syllable to wrong thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Then my Liege, this present evening</l>
                  <l>They have appoynted meeting in the garden:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> beleeve they are neare there already:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> shall attend your person to the place;</l>
                  <l>But then <hi>I</hi> hope youle graciously excuse</l>
                  <l>My absence; Ile wait within your call.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Come lets away. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:21"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Honorio <hi>and</hi> Fabianus <hi>at one doore,</hi> Princesse <hi>and</hi> Clara <hi>at the other.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas here I did appoynt him come: to which</l>
                  <l>He promised.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam see, he has already made a strict</l>
                  <l>Performance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorio</hi> you're punctuall in your word.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I esteeme a promise made to you</l>
                  <l>As a Religious vow taken before the Altar</l>
                  <l>Of the gods.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas no appointment 'twixt us two, but I</l>
                  <l>Suppos'd you were in person, as in love and duty,</l>
                  <l>Neer the Princesse.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>You were not certain then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>No, but as the needle of a Dyall</l>
                  <l>Toucht by the Adamant, though with trembling</l>
                  <l>It move to and fro, yet fixes not,</l>
                  <l>Till it attaine the North: so though I move,</l>
                  <l>And walke, yet by a sympathy in love,</l>
                  <l>Can never rest till I arrive your presence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon Lady my still labouring heart,</l>
                  <l>That like a Pinnace, toss'd on the curl'd waves</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Neptunes</hi> watry Empire, at such time,</l>
                  <l>When with his frowne he threatens destruction</l>
                  <l>To despairing Sea-men, wou'd gladly arrive</l>
                  <l>Some happy Haven where to rest secure,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>As how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>To finish up the summe of all my earthly</l>
                  <l>Happinesse i'th promise of your love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Were that the height of your conceived blisse?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and no heaven,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>I have heard that affection which can know</l>
                  <l>A fulnesse to its height, is never permanent:</l>
                  <l>"For loves noone is instant night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet a still growing desire to attaine that</l>
                  <l>Height argues a more firme affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:21"/>
                  <hi>King and</hi> Callidus <hi>behind the Arras.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>There they are my Liege;</l>
                  <l>Obscure your person, and grant me your Royall</l>
                  <l>Licence to depart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You have it: away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Suppose I shou'd give promise of my love,</l>
                  <l>By your owne argument you then were at</l>
                  <l>Your height, so must decline: Come I will not</l>
                  <l>Promise.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I like that well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Because I'de keep your love still growing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis too true: oh impudence unheard of.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Love's a child, and fondly desires first one</l>
                  <l>Thing, then another; and thinks no happinesse</l>
                  <l>Beyond what he craves; so I desire first</l>
                  <l>A promise of your love, which if you please</l>
                  <l>To grant, my fondling heart will still aspire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My life and kingdome next: oh villanous Traitor,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Excuse my modesty if I then bestow</l>
                  <l>This slight favour first to play withall, a kisse.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I am no longer able to containe—</l>
                  <l>Out Traytors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas 'tis we that are betray'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No; but by the gods deliver'd up to my just rage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>We're all undone for ever!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Though he be the King, whose sacred name</l>
                  <l>I bow to, he shall not dare to wrong you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Shou'd the gods themselves come wrapt</l>
                  <l>In terrour, I wou'd thus oppose 'hem <stage>both draws.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You were best commit an out-rage,</l>
                  <l>Where's our guard? Treason.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Callidus,</hi> drawes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>My gracious Liege, what</l>
                  <l>Villanous hand is that which is not blasted,</l>
                  <l>If lift a weapon 'gainst the sacred</l>
                  <l>Majesty of a King — oh misery! is it you</l>
                  <l>Attempt this traitorous act?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>We spit that name like poyson in their face,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:22"/>
                  <l>That dare accuse us: no, let him but gage</l>
                  <l>His royall word, not to execute his rage</l>
                  <l>On these; we'll lay our lives and weapons</l>
                  <l>At his feet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>If not, we vow to dye their Champions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Insolent Rebells.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile move the King for you — Sir I beseech You not to discharge your wrath against those Harmlesse Ladies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Move not for us alone, for heaven sake</l>
                  <l>Let him sacrifice us all together.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Sir smooth your brow, they'l not yield,</l>
                  <l>Except you promise not to wrong the Ladyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Think not treacherous villains, we promise</l>
                  <l>Not to hurt, 'cause we stand in feare of you:</l>
                  <l>We cou'd have come with armed men, that soone</l>
                  <l>Shou'd have chastis'd your bold usurping spirits,</l>
                  <l>But that I sham'd the aire shou'd know the</l>
                  <l>Foulnesse of the deed, my blood beares such an</l>
                  <l>Interest in it—upon mine honour Ile not touch 'hem.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Then to shew how much we scorne the name</l>
                  <l>Of Traitor: here on our bended knees we</l>
                  <l>Yield our weapons. <stage>Delivers their Swords.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What 'twixt the tender Motions of a father,</l>
                  <l>And their approved valour which we ought</l>
                  <l>To cherish, even in our enemies, I feele</l>
                  <l>My plyant heart yield to a calme discourse.</l>
                  <l>Stand up —</l>
                  <l>Tell me <hi>Honorio,</hi> sham'st thou not, that</l>
                  <l>Goodly wreath of Bayes, thy deserts</l>
                  <l>Did challenge to adorne thy brow, which seem'd.</l>
                  <l>More fresh and faire, then were the twining</l>
                  <l>Limbes of the <hi>Pienean</hi> Daphne shou'd now</l>
                  <l>Decay and wither: didst thou, a stranger,</l>
                  <l>Aide me 'gainst the Rebels of my State,</l>
                  <l>And plac't in my bosome prove thy selfe</l>
                  <l>A Traytor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Great sir, but heare me speak;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:22"/>
                  <l>If it be treason for a halfe-pin'd wretch,</l>
                  <l>When he attempteth food: if it be</l>
                  <l>Treason for that man who spends his life in</l>
                  <l>A vale of Teares, after some sad disaster,</l>
                  <l>When he sees a heaven plac't before him</l>
                  <l>And aspires to be seated there, then you</l>
                  <l>May stile my love and zeale to vertue</l>
                  <l>Treason: But if not, then pardon me, if</l>
                  <l>The whitenesse of my soule does animate</l>
                  <l>To tell you, 'tis not justice to oppose what</l>
                  <l>Fate and heaven decrees.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Let not your pride so farre transport you, that</l>
                  <l>You taxe our justice: 'tis not your wither'd</l>
                  <l>Bayes can protect you from our thunder, if</l>
                  <l>We please to strike—Though justice cou'd not blame</l>
                  <l>Him whose thoughts aspire to heaven; yet that</l>
                  <l>Presumptuous man, shou'd strive to plucke</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iove</hi> from his throne, to be enstal'd</l>
                  <l>A Deity himselfe, deserves in a flame of</l>
                  <l>Lightning to be cast to Hell, there to amaze</l>
                  <l>The damned.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Since no arguments can prevaile, take our</l>
                  <l>Lives, as sacrifice to your wrath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>And I beseech you, as you are my father,</l>
                  <l>To grant me this preferment, to be sent</l>
                  <l>Before 'hem: when we are immortall we shall</l>
                  <l>Enjoy more freely; and because I have</l>
                  <l>Not yet made promise of my love, J now</l>
                  <l>Doe vow—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>No; by that dreadfull <hi>Styx,</hi> by which the gods</l>
                  <l>Ne're sware, and broke their vow, I love him:</l>
                  <l>Nor shall my heart ever admit a change.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>I vow the like to thee</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Then 'twill be mercy if you take our lives.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>And send us to enjoy each other in <hi>Elizium.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No, you shall not obtaine that favour at</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:23"/>
                  <l>My hands—stand forth and heare your sentence.</l>
                  <l>For thee, thou staine to Princely blood, I doe</l>
                  <l>Confine to your lodging, on forfeit of your life—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Callidus</hi> she's your charge; let no private</l>
                  <l>Messages or meetings passe betwixt 'hem,</l>
                  <l>As you respect our favour: and for you</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorio</hi> and <hi>Fabianus,</hi> we sentence both</l>
                  <l>To banishment: and if after two dayes</l>
                  <l>You be seene within our Confines, we le</l>
                  <l>Have you mu'd up, and starv'd to death.</l>
                  <l>Goe, say we are mercifull you scapt</l>
                  <l>So well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What remaines for me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Fathers faithful service to us excuses you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>For Heavens sake sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Away, we'll heare no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets but speake before we part.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I say we'l heare no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Callidus!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>This is no time to talke, ith' morning</l>
                  <l>Ile procure a private meeting for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh thou ty'st us ever thine: farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Away with 'hem <hi>Callidus</hi>— you know your</l>
                  <l>Sentence, and your time. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Come <hi>Honorio,</hi> let us two goe finde</l>
                  <l>A way to death; no salve to cure the mind. <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACTƲS QƲARTƲS.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Callidus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>I Have promised this morning to give</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honorio</hi> and <hi>Fabianus</hi> accesse toth'</l>
                  <l>Princesse, which favour they esteeme as flowing</l>
                  <l>From my friend ship: which I but doe the more,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:23"/>
                  <l>To keepe my selfe still unsuspected by</l>
                  <l>The Princesse, who being immediate heire</l>
                  <l>To th' Crowne, might when the King's deceasd</l>
                  <l>Severely be reveng'd; 'twas about this time</l>
                  <l>I did appoynt 'hem come.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Honorio</hi> and <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>They are here already: my Noble frinds,</l>
                  <l>I attended for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>How fares the Princesse?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>And my love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas poore Ladyes almost spent with sorrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Deare friend, admit us to their sight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>That we may pay their teares with trebble</l>
                  <l>Interest; which if our eys, (their spring being</l>
                  <l>Dry) cannot afford, our hearts shall weepe</l>
                  <l>Blood, to recompence their sorrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>O friends, you know I hazard both my life</l>
                  <l>And Fortunes in this act: however, Ile not</l>
                  <l>Faile in what I promist: doe but with</l>
                  <l>Patience here expect a while, Ile bring</l>
                  <l>Them to you. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Our best friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>O yee gods, why d'yee mock mans frailty</l>
                  <l>With a seeming joy; then snatch it from him,</l>
                  <l>So to prove his ruine; first make beleeve</l>
                  <l>My selfe fixt in a heaven of blisse, betweene</l>
                  <l>A true love and a faithfull friend, then to</l>
                  <l>Be banish'd from my love, and cause my friend</l>
                  <l>Performes, but that to which the name doth bind,</l>
                  <l>(Being trust and secresie) to be a partner in</l>
                  <l>My sad Exile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Let not a thought of that raise trouble in</l>
                  <l>Thy breast: I know it is too narrow to containe</l>
                  <l>The griefe thy heart already is surcharg'd</l>
                  <l>Withall; and thou wilt wrong the more</l>
                  <l>Important cause, if shed a teare for me;</l>
                  <l>When all thou canst bestow will not suffice</l>
                  <l>To equall that pearly treasure which every</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:24"/>
                  <l>Houre the Princesse love causes her shed</l>
                  <l>For thee: See the Princesse and my love.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Princesse,</hi> and <hi>Clara,</hi> with <hi>Callidus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my dearest!</l>
                  <l>Let me flye into thy armes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fabianus!</hi> welcome to my bosome,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon</speaker>
                  <l>Upon this lip I will breath out my soule,</l>
                  <l>There leave it a surviving Trophy of</l>
                  <l>My true affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou shalt not leave thy soule without the</l>
                  <l>Substance of thy body: stay, in this kisse</l>
                  <l>Ile returne it thee agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Every conjunction of our lips, does</l>
                  <l>Propagate a soule, which we no sooner part,</l>
                  <l>But it is straight destroy'd; O let me bathe</l>
                  <l>Eternally in your bosome, and in a trance</l>
                  <l>Convey our selves into <hi>Elizium:</hi> then we'll</l>
                  <l>Implore the Deities inhabit, there to stay</l>
                  <l>Our spirits from returning backe to these</l>
                  <l>Sad prisons of our haplesse bodyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas my <hi>Clara,</hi> we must part; the breath</l>
                  <l>Of Kings is like the sentence of the gods,</l>
                  <l>Not to be avoyded.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou shalt not go: I will turne wood-Nymph,</l>
                  <l>And shroud my dearest under a grove of</l>
                  <l>Myrtle, free from the eye of vigilant</l>
                  <l>Suspition; and for thy guard, a thousand</l>
                  <l>Satyres, with their upright hornes</l>
                  <l>Shall stand about us, ready to assist thee</l>
                  <l>There, being free as our owne thoughts, we'll live</l>
                  <l>And love, and rest securely happy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>This thou maist fancy, but we nere attain to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Then Ile accompany my love—</l>
                  <l>Madam, shall we not?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes; the <hi>Grecian Argia</hi> cou'd for her husband</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Polynices</hi> body, being dead, travaile alone</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Thebes</hi> to give him buriall, and shall we</l>
                  <l>Leave our loves living: no, we'll alltogether sure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:24"/>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas your love arrives at impossibilities.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>True, for all passages are laid to prevent</l>
                  <l>Your flight: Madam, perswade your heart to let</l>
                  <l>Him goe; it may prove fortunate for all:</l>
                  <l>The King in time, and by my perswasions,</l>
                  <l>May be drawne to call 'hem from Exile: you</l>
                  <l>May be sure what I can doe shall ne're</l>
                  <l>Be wanting—To keep 'hem far enough <stage>Aside.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>For e're returning.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh thou true friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>A very true friend, and you knew all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Away, he is no friend to you, or me,</l>
                  <l>To bid me let you goe: <hi>Honorio</hi> thou shalt</l>
                  <l>Not; I will enchaine thee in my armes,</l>
                  <l>And to thy wrists fasten manicles of teares</l>
                  <l>To hold thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, this makes each minute but a sad Departure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Besides, the King will anon be stirring, and</l>
                  <l>Then you'le pluck new vengeance on</l>
                  <l>Your heads; alas I speak out of sincere</l>
                  <l>Affection I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace Screech-Owle, no mans voyce seemes</l>
                  <l>Other, that speaks with an intent to part us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, strive to suppresse this passion, and</l>
                  <l>Let patience, the good mans remedy in</l>
                  <l>Affliction crowne the end of all your sorrowes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh misery past humane sufferance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Thinke not so my dearest; 'tis harder</l>
                  <l>To conceive, than undergoe. Come <hi>Fabianus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let us take our leaves—thus—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand off, and come not neare me at this</l>
                  <l>Distance: Ile strengthen my imagination</l>
                  <l>With thy forme; then when thou art gone</l>
                  <l>I may retaine thy perfect Idea in my sight;</l>
                  <l>Thus—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas your passion forces you to an extasie;</l>
                  <l>These are but fancies urg'd by your height of</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:25"/>
                  <l>Sorrow; collect your scatter'd sences: thus</l>
                  <l>On your lips I seale my hearts contract.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>With these teares it shall be writ—</l>
                  <l>So bid me not farewell, nor will I you,</l>
                  <l>Least so we send a dart to kill each other:</l>
                  <l>But turne thou silent that way—</l>
                  <l>My griefes shall lead me this,</l>
                  <l>And may my love a happy harbour find</l>
                  <l>These teares the Ocean and my sighes the wind, <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clara</hi> we must part too the Princesse</l>
                  <l>Has already taught us how: farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Let all such lovers, as are crost by Fate,</l>
                  <l>Learne here to mourne at our unhappy state. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Friends 'twere not manly to let my tears</l>
                  <l>Expresse my sorrow; no my heart bleeds inward</l>
                  <l>At this sad departure: farewell, farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon, &amp; Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell our dearest friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha ha. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my sad heart, whither will the current</l>
                  <l>Of my griefes transport thee? my soule</l>
                  <l>Being fled and left my body, like a</l>
                  <l>Sepulchrall Statue, fixt here bereft of sence,</l>
                  <l>Onely knowing how to mourne; me thinks</l>
                  <l>The fabricke of the earth should tremble,</l>
                  <l>The heavens be clouded in a vaile of sables,</l>
                  <l>And weep it selfe in shoures upon the earth;</l>
                  <l>The Sunne goe shroud it selfe beneath the lower</l>
                  <l>World, never to rise againe; but cause an</l>
                  <l>Universall darknesse o're the earth, where</l>
                  <l>Men shall sit mourning our sad departure:</l>
                  <l>What can be left for two, so much distress'd,</l>
                  <l>But death, the period of each mans affliction;</l>
                  <l>That most unkindly flyes those whose griefes</l>
                  <l>Wou'd entertaine him; and surely strikes there</l>
                  <l>(Where but nam'd) they startle?—Friend, why</l>
                  <l>Doe we stand, as if we grew fixt here,</l>
                  <l>And cou'd not move.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Can he which beares a burthen, wou'd erac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:25"/>
                  <l>The Poles of heaven, to sustaine the weight, move</l>
                  <l>To, and fro, bearing that load about him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>I must acknowledge you a cause of sorrow</l>
                  <l>Wou'd force the Genius of the world into</l>
                  <l>A frenzie; yet mine's as great, 'cause 'tis</l>
                  <l>For me you suffer; but we, that like well-</l>
                  <l>Fenced Bulwarks, have together stood the</l>
                  <l>Shock of warre, when loud-mouth'd Canons</l>
                  <l>Breath'd destruction to an army shou'd</l>
                  <l>Scorne to fall as combatants in the Campe</l>
                  <l>Of love: no, lets with courage goe</l>
                  <l>Bravely on to meet our Fate: hope has</l>
                  <l>Not quite forsook us; as we passe I will</l>
                  <l>Relate somewhat may concerne us both—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Philomusus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>My Noble friends! whither now? no object</l>
                  <l>But the earth, what Cloud is this spread o're your</l>
                  <l>Face, that dimmes the wonted lustre of your</l>
                  <l>Eyes? by all that's Noble let me know, or</l>
                  <l>Ile repent I ere was nam'd your friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe not conjure us by so strict a charme,</l>
                  <l>We shall but make you miserable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>There's not that act, except it decline from</l>
                  <l>Honour, has power to make me poorer in</l>
                  <l>A thought.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Then know we two are banished.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Banished! why Ile be banish'd too then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>O no; stay you, and be happy in your Prince his love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not stay— say, what's the cause?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>If you will with us as I goe I shall relate</l>
                  <l>The story; but you must in disguise, or</l>
                  <l>Youl'le be stay'd; and you shall find ere long,</l>
                  <l>I had little cause to feare being banished:</l>
                  <l>But since we must from our best retreat,</l>
                  <l>Let Passive valour be as th' Active, great. <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:26"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Pupillus, Mercutio, Plod, <hi>and</hi> Fled-wit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray Gentlemen, were you inspired, as you say I must bee, before you came to be a Courtier, and a Wit?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>No question.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>And d'ee thinke 'tis possible for me to be made one too?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell you sir, before these gentlemen your friends, and mine, Ile undertake to furnish you with as much wit as shall serve for a Country Justice, or an Aldermans heire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Why that's enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>But then you must be confident of its operation, part free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with any thing that shall be requested of you in the act; not as an Usurer payes Subsidies, grudgingly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, I scorne it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Had it not beene pitty, one of your estate and Fortune shou'd have knowne no recreation, but going a mile out of town, with a company of Codsheads, to be drunke with Creame and Stewd-Pruines.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O they are delicate with Rose-water and Sugar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Poxe on't, Bawdy-house fare: No, after your inspiration you may revell with this Lady, discourse with that Lady, and what you will with the third Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh I am almost inspired at the conceit on it: pray let be done, while I am in the aspiring fit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>It shall sir— Doe you heare <hi>Tom,</hi> goe and prepare <hi>Flavia</hi> for the project, and bring those properties we agreed on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Say no more. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Whither doe you send him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>To an Antiquaries study; for strange properties to perform the Ceremonies requisite at inspiration: for we must use Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Incantations, Conjurations, Imprecations, and all for the rare effect of Inspiration.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Blesse me, doe you begin to conjure already?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>No, he tells you but what he must doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>But harke you; pray d'ee deale with honest, faire conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Devills?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>O blemish to our sacred Magicke—Devills!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O no, pray Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:26"/>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>That thought's enough to ruine all the fabricke of our hopes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Good sir, Ile never thinke while I live agen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell you sir, we must invoake the Celestiall Deities— We may beginne the Act, none but the bright <hi>Minerva</hi> can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>And will she come at your call.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, if you performe quietly what we desire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh most obedient Goddesse.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Plod</hi> with a Boxe, in which are little pieces of paper rold up: A Table set forth.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you come? 'tis well: Is <hi>Flavia</hi> ready?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>Onely waits her Cue</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Look you sir, you see these papers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I, whence came they; from the Lottery?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>No sir, they are certaine Collections out of learned and witty Authors, for all humours in an accomplished wit. Now sir, you must eate every one of hem one by one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>How, eate 'hem?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>I ease 'hem, and you shall find they will produce effects as various, as the qualities or conditions out of whom they were collected: now therefore off with your Hat and Cloake, kneele downe with a strong beliefe, imagination, and attention — you two stand to keepe him in that equall posture I shall set him; so, now first with a Scholastique Inspiration: somewhat of a hard digesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>"Dulcia non meruit qui non gustavit amara.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O 'twill never downe, I shall be choakt with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>My life Sir we'll helpe it downe—here—so—feare not, I warrant you—is it downe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Almost—so,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>How is it sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O 'twas so sweete at first, and so abhominable bitter at the last—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer</speaker>
                  <p>Why there you relish the conceit sir: for the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it is; Hee deserves not sweete, that has not tasted bitter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:27"/>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I have tasted a bitter one; now pray let the next be a sweet one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>According as we see this work: 'thas a present operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on—How doe you feele your selfe inclin'd?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh I cou'd quarrell about the Etymologie of words, fight about Syllables, and Orthography, chop Logique with my Father, Write Tragedies and Comedies by the grosse: and my fingers itch at an Hen-roost.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>'Thas wrought bravely, the direct symptomes of an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity wit: now for the inspiration of a confident Poeticall wit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray pick out the hard words, if there be any.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>There's none in this — you shall heare it.</l>
                  <l>"This from our Author I was bid to say,</l>
                  <l>"By <hi>Iove</hi> 'tis good; and if you lik't you may.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile tell you how I like it presently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Come sir, downe with it—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>So, this past with ease—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>How doe you find your selfe affected now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh that I were in a Play-house—I wou'd tell the whole Audience of their pittifull, Hereticall, Criticall humours—Let a man, striving to enrich his labours, make himselfe as poore as a broken Citizen, that dares not so much as shew the tips on's Hornes: yet will these people crye it downe, they know not why: One loves high language, though he understands it not; another whats obscaene, to move the blood, not spleene: a third, whose wit lyes all in his gall, must have a Satyre: a fourth man all ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: and the fift man not knowing what to have, grounds his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion on the next man ith' formall Ruffe; and so many heads, so many severall humours; and yet the poor Poet must find waies to please 'hem all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>It workes strangely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>But when they shal come to feed on the Offalls of wit, have nothing for their money but a Drumme, a Fooles Coat, and Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder; see Comedies, more ridiculous than a Morrice dance; and for their Tragedies, about at Cudgells were a brave Battalia to 'hem: Oh <hi>Phoebus, Phoebus,</hi> what will this world come to?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>'Fore <hi>Iove,</hi> it has wrought most strangely—Tis well here we're none but friends—how doe you sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:27"/>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! pretty, pretty, sure I have talked extravagantly, Gentlemen have I not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>I indeed have you; 'tis of a delicate operation: Now sir, you shall have a valiant inspiration to confront your enemy, or rivall in your Mistresses favour—In this paper is the expiring breath of a great warriour, the last words he utter'd.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>"—Farewell light,</l>
                     <l>"Tis fit the world should weare eternall night.</l>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Why this will kill me sure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>No, hold him fast—tis of a strong operation—So, chew it well, feare nothing—Now it is downe: how is't?</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>He breakes violently from them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me goe, let me goe, the world's too narrow to confine me: Ile mount the skies, snatch <hi>Ioves</hi> three-fold lightning from his hand, dart it at the World, and reduc't againe to its first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate Chaos, drye up the Sea with fire of my rage, and puffe mens soules away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>We must change this humour: Ile now beleeve a strong imagination's witch-craft: force downe another; read it first: What is't? hold him fast.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <l>"Enter these Armes, and since thou thoughtst it best,</l>
                  <l>"Not to dreame all my dreame, lets act the rest.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>A fit one, a wanton lovers rapture: give it him, thrust it downe: So, he begins to yield; how is't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O what have you gi'n me now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer,</speaker>
                  <p>Onely to inspire you with a wanton art to winne your Mistris.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Tis wonderfull provocative, believe me: sure it came out of <hi>Ovids-Ars-Amandi:</hi> oh for the book of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis,</hi> to Court my Mistris by: I cou'd dye, I cou'd dye in the <hi>Eli-zi-um</hi> of her Armes: no sweets to those of Love: O Love, love, thy flames will burne me up to dust and ashes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>We must quench your flames— Pinch him hard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Harder yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh—</l>
                  <l>What doe you doe? what doe you? Alas all's downe againe;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:28"/>
                  <l>I am as cold as a Cucumber.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer</speaker>
                  <l>So, I beleeve you are sufficiently prepared:</l>
                  <l>Now we will invoke the goddesse <hi>Minerva</hi>— kneele,</l>
                  <l>Downe with your face to the west: harken with</l>
                  <l>Attention to what she shall say or request, and be sure to performe it —So, 'tis well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Does she come yet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, he must invoak first.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou sacred goddesse of <hi>Joves</hi> brave begot, <stage>walk round about him.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Descend to earth, and here make fast the knot</l>
                  <l>We humble Mortalls have begunne to tye,</l>
                  <l>And we'll adore thy glorious Deity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O me, O.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Soft Musick. Enter <hi>Flavia</hi> drest like <hi>Minerva</hi> with a Violl of Water.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Who calls <hi>Minerva</hi> from the Starry Court?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh 'twas he Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>We know the full effects of your desire,</l>
                  <l>It is this noble youth with wit t'inspire:</l>
                  <l>Then downe his throat this sacred drinke compell,</l>
                  <l>Tis salt, and water from the Muses well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Paugh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Now let him offer gold to our dispose,</l>
                  <l>And all's confirm'd with this one pluck by th'nose.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O me—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>What gold have you about you—quickly, quickly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Onely twenty peeces in my fob.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Dis-fob 'em quickly, and present 'hem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Please you Madam, here's forty Angels to wait on your Lady-ship to heaven agen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>We doe accept 'hem—so live ever blest:</l>
                  <l>I must ascend to my <hi>Aetheriall</hi> rest. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>So, rise up, all's done: now be confident, and you shall prove a Wit—all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>But harke you gentlemen: pray what does she doe with money?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Releeves poore Poets, that eats Oads, And Madrigalls: Come lets to the next Taverne, and drinke her health.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:28"/>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <l>Come then—Nay now I am inspir'd,</l>
                  <l>I will doe things shall make me be admir'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>There's a touch of his Poeticall inspiration. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>King, Princesse, Clara, Marania, Moronzo,</hi> and <hi>Callidus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Is <hi>Honorio</hi> and <hi>Fabianus</hi> shipt and gone?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <p>They are my Liege.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King</speaker>
                  <l>Tis well: methinkes the aire seems purer since</l>
                  <l>They both departed: sure if they had stay'd</l>
                  <l>Their trechrous breath wou'd have infected</l>
                  <l>My whole Kingdome—But thou, degenerate from</l>
                  <l>All Princely blood, still mournest their absence,</l>
                  <l>And with effeminate teares wou'dst move</l>
                  <l>My pitty to call 'hem from Exile: no,</l>
                  <l>Sooner shalt thou call backe Time, than move</l>
                  <l>A thought in me shall yield to't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <p>Deare Father move the King.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile blast him dumbe that names 'hem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>No hope, you see the King's resolv'd—My Liege</l>
                  <l>The Lord <hi>Philomusus</hi> is secretly stolne away</l>
                  <l>With them in disguise.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Torture to my soule, it cannot be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <p>I can assure your Majesty 'tis so.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh where's that Subject that a King dares love?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philomusus</hi> gone—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Leave this sullen humour <hi>Dulcimenta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or by just heavens I will disclaime you mine;</l>
                  <l>Though youth and errour lead you to a fault,</l>
                  <l>(Which I may study to forget, upon conformance</l>
                  <l>Of your will with mine) will you pursue</l>
                  <l>The cause, and peevishly consume your selfe</l>
                  <l>In teares, for him whom the gods themselves</l>
                  <l>Doe hate, for spotted treason gainst your Fathers</l>
                  <l>Person; it cou'd be no lesse when he attempted</l>
                  <l>To match the Kingdomes heire—goe to, raise</l>
                  <l>Not my fury to that height, which if it fall,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:29"/>
                  <l>Shall crush you to your ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, thinke not a disobedient passion guides</l>
                  <l>My will to love or hate, contrary to your</l>
                  <l>Mind; but since 'tis so, heaven has it selfe decree'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Away, taxe not the heavens with what's unjust</l>
                  <l>They ne're decreed the blood of Kings should</l>
                  <l>Mixe with Traytors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, they were no Traytors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis well, defend 'hem still.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>No, their innocence will do't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Very good; I perceive from whence this</l>
                  <l>Springs; your company with <hi>Clara</hi> feeds this</l>
                  <l>Rebellious spirit, does it? I have an easie cure for that:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>onzo</hi> keepe your daughters to you; there's</l>
                  <l>Neither of 'hem we'le admit to attend her, since</l>
                  <l>Favour is abus'd, we can restrain it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>Their lives and mine are prostrate to your will.</l>
                  <l>Come daughters—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay: Sir has tyrannie usurpt the seat of</l>
                  <l>Mercy in your royall breast: if so, let death</l>
                  <l>Part us, and so end our woe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe beseech you, as you are my Father,</l>
                  <l>By your wonted love to me, or whatsoe're</l>
                  <l>You hold more deare, bereave me not both of</l>
                  <l>My love and friend together; this cruelty</l>
                  <l>Exceeds the former; lover is a name may</l>
                  <l>Be in time dispenc'd with; but a friend, oh,</l>
                  <l>A true friend, heaven knowes not a happinesse</l>
                  <l>Beyond it: deare sit, by my dead mothers ashes,</l>
                  <l>Which were you neare, wou'd (in imitation of</l>
                  <l>Those amorous twines which did inchaine</l>
                  <l>Your hearts) flye up, and hang about you,</l>
                  <l>Gently to chide this most unnaturall act:</l>
                  <l>Which, because distance of place denyes it,</l>
                  <l>Send but to know, and you shall heare</l>
                  <l>The Marble Tombe weeps at this disaster.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>The remembrance of her dead mother</l>
                  <l>Wou'd stir my pitty, shou'd I not resist it:</l>
                  <l>I must suddenly <hi>Callidus,</hi> convey our</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:29"/>
                  <l>Daughter to her lodging; we'll appoynt</l>
                  <l>Some other Ladies to attend her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, we are resolv'd: <hi>Moronzo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Performe what we command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>I shall my Liege: come daughters.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Lead on. <stage>Ex. severally.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACTƲS QƲINTƲS.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Mercutio, Pupillus, Fled-wit, Plod,</hi> and <hi>Flavia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>HOw? and how stands the businesse?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, you know best.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Perceive you not an alteration, or transmutation in my outward person?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thinks your words fall off your tongue with a more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Thinke so: be wise and catch 'hem as they fall: they may inspire you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>You are strangely metamorphos'd since I saw you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mutor pro temporum ratione,</hi> as the learned say.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>That's the fruit of his Scholastique inspiration.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>O Lady, if your heart bestone, I wou'd 'twere broke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>I have heard men wish their Mistris heart wounded, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver broke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Pshew, my love is not like other mens, that will whine and crye, looke pale, and weare night caps: no, my love is a bouncing love, and makes no more of cracking a Ladyes heart, than a Squirrell of a Nut.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>A notable crack.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>For harke you a word in your care (I wou'd not have these Gentlemen know it) I am inspired.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Now by <hi>Diana</hi> is it true?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:30"/>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>I have sed it, be wise and have me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>O you men have such strange wayes to play upon poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, there's but one way I'de play upon you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>And will dissemble most egregiously.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Who I dissemble? why these Gentlemen will sweare all my acts are simple.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay Lady, I know he has not a thought but what is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly innocent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>If you'll but marry me, there is not that desire, or incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which you shall have; but I will strive with my best part to satisfie: what wou'd you more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>I must confesse you promise faire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>And will performe as well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas my Virgin feares bid me I shou'd not yield.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>A poxe of your Virginity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not what to doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, I know what to doe, and you'le say but I once.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, it can be no blemish to your modest Vertue, to yield your love at first to one, whose Worth and fortunes equall yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then I wholly yield me yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>That's well said, this kisse in earnest; come, we'll not stand long upon the businesse, but bee marryed presently: I must provide Ribbond for all the Courtiers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>You may save that cost; their hats are so stuff'd with Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons already, they'll finde no roome to weare 'hem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup.</speaker>
                  <p>Poxe 'tis a French fashion: I warrant there are some wou'd change their very faces with a French man to be a <hi>la mode,</hi> but come, you two shal lead the Bride, and you shall give her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall command us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pup,</speaker>
                  <p>Soe, soe. <hi>Hymen!</hi> O <hi>Hymen</hi> snuffe thy torch and see A paire of Lovers, leads their way to me. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:30"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Princesse <hi>and</hi> Lady.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Whither is compassion fled, that should</l>
                  <l>Inhabit in the breasts of men, and make</l>
                  <l>Distinction 'twixt their knowing soules, and</l>
                  <l>Sencelesse cruelty of savage beasts, guided</l>
                  <l>By their wills to ruine, not reason, how, or whom;</l>
                  <l>When he that beares the title of a King,</l>
                  <l>And Father, can nor find mercy in the one,</l>
                  <l>Nor love ith' other: oh you sad lovers that are</l>
                  <l>Crost by Fortune, and your Parents hate, come</l>
                  <l>Pay your floods of teares, as tribute</l>
                  <l>To my sorrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam be pleas'd to retire and repose your</l>
                  <l>Selfe; sorrow and want of rest must needs impaire</l>
                  <l>Your health: thinke not because she, whom</l>
                  <l>You please to honour with the name of friend,</l>
                  <l>Is taken from you, that none is left true</l>
                  <l>And faithfull to attend you; yes, I am one,</l>
                  <l>Though young in service to you, would (if made</l>
                  <l>Happy ith' triall) embrace a danger, to</l>
                  <l>Assure your quiet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <p>Can this be reall?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, as your griefes are true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Is there one left faithfull to attend me</l>
                  <l>Now my <hi>Clara's</hi> gone? If so, prethee</l>
                  <l>Conduct me to some gloomy vale,</l>
                  <l>Wrapt with unpleasant shades of Yew</l>
                  <l>And Cypres, sprung up from lovers graves:</l>
                  <l>On which the croaking Raven, with other Birds</l>
                  <l>Of night may sit and hollow sad accents;</l>
                  <l>Such as may fitly simpathize with mourning:</l>
                  <l>A murmuring brooke of wronged Virgins teares,</l>
                  <l>That may glide softly by, and receive mine,</l>
                  <l>To augment their streames: a bed of Mosse,</l>
                  <l>Gather'd from Vaults and Charnells, where</l>
                  <l>The dead inhabit, to repose us on, there</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:31"/>
                  <l>Thou and I will sit and feed on sorrow,</l>
                  <l>That shall feede on us, and when we</l>
                  <l>Both are dead, some distracted Muse fled</l>
                  <l>To those groves, shall in an uncouth</l>
                  <l>Tone sing our sad Requiems.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                  <l>I was plac'd by your father, in hope I might</l>
                  <l>Have remov'd this passion; but your discourse</l>
                  <l>Makes me an object rather to incite you mourne,</l>
                  <l>Then otherwise: let me intreate your highnesse sit</l>
                  <l>And repose your selfe: Ile trye my voyce to charme</l>
                  <l>Your eyes and heart with pleasing slumbers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Most willingly, some rest in sorrow will do</l>
                  <l>Well—Begin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <stage>Song.</stage>
                     <lg>
                        <l>CHarme, oh charme, thou god of sleep,</l>
                        <l>Her faire eyes, that waking mourne;</l>
                        <l>Frightfull visions from her keep,</l>
                        <l>Such as are by sorrowes borne:</l>
                        <l>But let all the sweets that may</l>
                        <l>Wait on rest, her thoughts obey.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Flye: oh flye, thou god of love,</l>
                        <l>To that breast thy dart did wound,</l>
                        <l>Draw thy shaft, the smart remove,</l>
                        <l>Let her wonted joyes be found:</l>
                        <l>Raise up pleasure to a flood,</l>
                        <l>Never ebbing; new joyes bud.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <l>So my Charmes have tooke, poore Lady</l>
                  <l>She has not enjoy'd so much quiet rest,</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Honorio</hi> and <hi>Fabianus</hi> left</l>
                  <l>The Court. <stage>Enter <hi>Callidus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis I Lady: How fares the Princesse?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak lower, she's asleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Good heaven be prais'd, she may in time</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:31"/>
                  <l>Forget her griefes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                  <l>Not till the King forget his cruelty:</l>
                  <l>I dare not say the name of King gives</l>
                  <l>It a more modest title.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>I must confesse, 'tis little lesse—but Subjects</l>
                  <l>Must not see, much lesse say, what mis-becomes</l>
                  <l>Their Prince; 'tis enough we performe what they</l>
                  <l>Command, not question why.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my <hi>Clara:</hi> oh my <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                  <l>Shee wakes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that <hi>Callidus?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes Madam, the King commanded me to give</l>
                  <l>Your Highnesse notice, last night Embassadours</l>
                  <l>Came from <hi>Portingall</hi> to <hi>Naples,</hi> and the King</l>
                  <l>Hath already given them both audience and</l>
                  <l>Their answer, and they are making a speedy</l>
                  <l>Returne backe from whence they came, the</l>
                  <l>Reason of their comming or businesse I understand</l>
                  <l>Not: but 'tis his Majesties pleasure you instantly</l>
                  <l>Repaire to him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>More corrasive: well, my duty binds me</l>
                  <l>To awaite his pleasure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>I shall attend your highnesse.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>My sad soule presages some new affliction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                  <l>Take comfort gracious Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no rest I ever hope to have,</l>
                  <l>Till heaven decrees I rest within my grave. <stage>Ex. omn.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>King, Moronzo,</hi> and others.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lords, what think you of the match</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the Prince of <hi>Portingall,</hi> and our daughter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>Without question my Liege, 'twill prove</l>
                  <l>Fortunate for both, if the Princesse</l>
                  <l>Can be drawne to affect him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I make no question but to winne her to't:</l>
                  <l>Are the Ambassadours return'd for <hi>Portingall?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>They are my Liege.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:32"/>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis well, we expect his arrivall suddainly:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moronzo,</hi> let it be your charge to see all things</l>
                  <l>Correspond so great an entertainment—</l>
                  <l>Where's <hi>Callidus?</hi> we sent him to attend</l>
                  <l>Our daughter hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Princesse, Callidus,</hi> and <hi>Lady.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>They are here my Liege.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What mourning!</l>
                  <l>This habit ill becomes you, knowing it contradicts</l>
                  <l>Our will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon me sir, it best sutes my thoughts,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>It best sutes the blacknesse of your disobedience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, name but that thing, rests in my power to</l>
                  <l>Divert your anger, my duty shall lend me wings,</l>
                  <l>On which Ile flye to act.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Your speeches are but aire, there's no performance:</l>
                  <l>You insult too much upon the softnesse of my temper:</l>
                  <l>But heare me now with that attention thou</l>
                  <l>Wou'dst an Oracle, pronouncing of thy fate,</l>
                  <l>What my will decrees.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>If death, I shall embrace it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Then briefly thus, <hi>Portingalls</hi> great King</l>
                  <l>Our late enemy, Fame reporting what</l>
                  <l>Thou least deserv'st, vertue and obedience,</l>
                  <l>Has by Embassadours, 'twixt you, our Kingdomes</l>
                  <l>Heire, and his sonne, treated of a match;</l>
                  <l>Whereof (because 'twill be a meanes to unite</l>
                  <l>Our Kingdomes, which have beene long at variance)</l>
                  <l>We have accepted, and return'd this answer,</l>
                  <l>That if he please in person to come for you,</l>
                  <l>He shou'd enjoy you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>O my Prophetique soule!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>This will make sure for ever against <hi>Honorio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Fabianus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Thinke but the danger will ensue, if you refuse:</l>
                  <l>First, to mock the expectation of a King</l>
                  <l>Can bring no lesse than warre upon our</l>
                  <l>Now peacefull Kingdome: next, the shame</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:32"/>
                  <l>Of forraigne nations: and lastly, my curse</l>
                  <l>Pursues thee to thy grave, if thou refuse:</l>
                  <l>Thinke on't, theres no delay, the Prince will with</l>
                  <l>Speed be here, and claime our promise:</l>
                  <l>Therefore let your face beare smiles, to expresse</l>
                  <l>His welcome; if your obedience will prompt you</l>
                  <l>To doe this, you shall, besides the height of</l>
                  <l>Happinesse in so blest an union, enjoy againe</l>
                  <l>The company of <hi>Clara,</hi> the freedome of</l>
                  <l>A Queene, and all the pleasures earth can bestow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>And all wil prove but torment without <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>She's ith' same note still.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dulcimenta,</hi> you know our will,</l>
                  <l>Which if not perform'd, <stage>Exit <hi>King,</hi> cum alijs, man. <hi>Prin.</hi> and <hi>Lady.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>By all my hopes, I sweare thy Fates decree'd,</l>
                  <l>My curse pursues thy soule, thy heart shall bleed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Every houre creates but a new torment.</l>
                  <l>Was ever cruelty like this? is't not enough</l>
                  <l>To banish him I love, but force my affection</l>
                  <l>On another? rob me of my blisse, and not</l>
                  <l>Afford me quietly to mourne: in what</l>
                  <l>A strange Dilemma is my soule perplext?</l>
                  <l>Death I meet, whether I refuse or yield:</l>
                  <l>Which of those two instruct me Love;</l>
                  <l>If J yield, 'twill be a death Mortality,</l>
                  <l>Knowes not to sustaine; because to live</l>
                  <l>With one J cannot love: if deny, 'twill</l>
                  <l>Be an easier death; but then a curse</l>
                  <l>Will make my paines eternall: say J</l>
                  <l>Avoyd the curse, and match this forraine Prince,</l>
                  <l>The curse of Lovers will pursue me</l>
                  <l>For the breach of faith:</l>
                  <l>On then, J am resolv'd, Jle rather dye,</l>
                  <l>Curs'd for my faith, than for inconstancy. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Mercutio, Plod, Fled-wit,</hi> and <hi>Flavia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha, ha, he's as foxt within, as a Constable by mid-night:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:33"/>
                  <l>Thou hast him sure wench now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>As fast as the Parsons tongue, and Their consents could bind 'hem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Now thou must remember thy Benefactors in the dayes of thy prosperity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <p>We shall share I hope in your good fortunes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>Even all alike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>That's well said.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>De'e heare gentlemen, you have draind him pretty well al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, bin paid for your labours—Beleeve it, you have all you are like to have of him, or me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, thou dost but jest wench.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall finde I speak in very good earnest: If a supper, and a sack posset can content you, you shal be welcome; for any other matter, you see the interest you are like to have of him or me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Canst thou so wickedly forget thy friends?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>No sir, 'twill prove vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Canst thou name that thing cal'd vertue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes sir, and will learne to practice it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>The devill thou canst.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Patience sir, in this case, will prove your best</l>
                  <l>Remedy: You have my resolution Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>And so farewell. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <p>Poxe goe wi' you, and all the dissembling generation of you—Now Gentlemen where's our dinners, sack, and wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; our mid-night revells, and what not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <p>Guld by a woman: now the curse of an insatiate desire pursue 'hem all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plod.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets home, and study mischiefe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>No faith, lets learne to live better,</l>
                  <l>And goe sober to bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fled.</speaker>
                  <l>That we shall never doe. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:33"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> King, Moronzo, Callidus, <hi>with Attendants, at one side of the Stage, a Lord disguised, as Prince of</hi> Portingall, Honorio, Fabianus, Philomusus <hi>disguised as At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants at the other.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Cease Musicke.</l>
                  <l>Welcome great Prince to <hi>Naples,</hi> and so</l>
                  <l>Are all about you. <stage>A shout.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <p>The people second it with acclamations of their joy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>The bounty of your Kingly love transcends our Expectation or desert.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <p>Our power attaines not the performance of our will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>If you strive to out-vye friendly expressions,</l>
                  <l>My stocke of language will not extend to see't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I have.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Great sir, how fares your Princely daughter,</l>
                  <l>Whom Fame reports fitter to consort with</l>
                  <l>Angels, than to match Mortality.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You'll find fame has beene too lavish sir—</l>
                  <l>Call forth our daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Princesse, Clara, Marania,</hi> and <hi>Lady.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Aurora</hi> blushing proclaimes the day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah me!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Why sigh you Lady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>To think a Prince shou'd come to sue</l>
                  <l>For what I cannot grant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>How's this? is her affection plac't else where?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Were it so, no doubt you have Oratory sufficient</l>
                  <l>To divert it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>I did beleeve you had before we came prepar'd</l>
                  <l>Her heart to give us entertainment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I did; and thought your presence would have</l>
                  <l>Remov'd all obstacles to hinder your enjoying—</l>
                  <l>Away thou scorne of time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:34"/>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>This strange and unexpected—Your patience Sir,</l>
                  <l>Ile trye my fate—Lady it should seeme you</l>
                  <l>Have already dispos'd your love: Ile not dispute the</l>
                  <l>Worth of him you have pleas'd to make so happy:</l>
                  <l>But behold I bring a heart, fraught with as true</l>
                  <l>Affection, as ever man could boast; a title too</l>
                  <l>That may deserve you: refuse me not, 'twas fame</l>
                  <l>First tooke my eare, your beauty now my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Wou'd I had lesse of both, since both prove so unhappy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis you make 'hem so; demolish not with sorrow</l>
                  <l>Such a beauty, as were enough for all your sexe▪</l>
                  <l>And make 'hem proud to know 'twas part of yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Retaine this language for those whose height</l>
                  <l>Of love can meete your flame; tis vainly</l>
                  <l>Bestow'd on me; my heart's already fixt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me rip out that heart, the Cabinet</l>
                  <l>Of rebellious thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>Good sir, give not so much scope to fury.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>To take all cause of further sute away,</l>
                  <l>Receive my story and resolves in one:</l>
                  <l>Then let him sacrifice my heart to love,</l>
                  <l>And I shall live triumphant after death,</l>
                  <l>Dying that causes Martyr, however,</l>
                  <l>Great Prince, deeme not a Ladyes worth impair'd,</l>
                  <l>When I declare I lov'd beneath my birth.</l>
                  <l>My father, at his returne from warre,</l>
                  <l>And bright Conquest shining on his sword,</l>
                  <l>Brought with him one, whom he himselfe</l>
                  <l>Esteem'd the mirrour of valour, and heroicke acts;</l>
                  <l>His name <hi>Honorio,</hi> whose descent unnam'd,</l>
                  <l>None knew from whence, except the child of Fame:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Noble Stranger's</hi> merit wonne my heart,</l>
                  <l>And so we two grew of one faith, one mind,</l>
                  <l>Till adverse fortune envying our blisse,</l>
                  <l>We were betray'd; he banish'd from me,</l>
                  <l>And I alone left to deplore my fate:</l>
                  <l>Now let all know, by heaven's I'me fixt, nere</l>
                  <l>To enjoy another.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:34"/>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent Lady! I take you at your word; <stage>discovers.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thus receive your onely true <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! where?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                  <l>So, I must resigne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Here in me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>How's this!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>For firmer proofe, see <hi>Fabianus</hi> here. <stage>
                        <hi>Fab.</hi> discovers,</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Amazement seazes me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus I bring home a true love to my <hi>Clara,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A loyall Subject to my Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>My dearest love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh are these joyes essentiall?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Our Guard there, off with their heads: doe you mocke</l>
                  <l>Our fury with impostures?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>They deserve your utmost rage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>How—Stay your fury till you have a cause.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prin.</speaker>
                  <l>May I beleeve this happinesse?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis a truth as reall as we thus embrace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Fabianus</hi> live I to enjoy thy love!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou dost; on thy lip I doe confirme my blisse.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Are not you that same <hi>Honorio,</hi> whom</l>
                  <l>I exild with <hi>Fabianus</hi> there?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And dare you set foote upon our Confines</l>
                  <l>After such a Censure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, but not as <hi>Honorio</hi> onely; but as Prince</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Portingall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>How, you Prince of <hi>Portingall?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>As sure as you are King of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>It cannot be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>By Circumstance Ile mak't appeare:</l>
                  <l>The fame of this blest Lady, spred through</l>
                  <l>My Fathers Court, wing'd my desires to view</l>
                  <l>So much perfection; which made me take</l>
                  <l>Occasion of your present warre, to insinuate</l>
                  <l>My selfe in favour of you and of the Court,</l>
                  <l>But durst not presume discovery, by reason of</l>
                  <l>The unhappy difference 'twixt our Kingdomes,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:35"/>
                  <l>(The cause whereof has beene related) then at the height</l>
                  <l>Of happinesse, some envious fate possess'd you</l>
                  <l>With the knowledge of our loves, so banish us:</l>
                  <l>In whose supposed Exile, this noble Lord became a <stage>Philomusus discovers.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Willing partner, and I bare him with me</l>
                  <l>To my Fathers Court; which that 'tis truth</l>
                  <l>He's able to enforme you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, upon the safety of my life he speaks all truth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Dost thou confirme it <hi>Philomusus?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then 'twere sinne to beare the least suspition;</l>
                  <l>Be neare us, thou deserv'st more honour than</l>
                  <l>We can bestow—Pardon great Prince the</l>
                  <l>Severity of our anger 'gainst your person</l>
                  <l>When you were unknowne: but in requitall,</l>
                  <l>Here receive our daughter, with free consent,</l>
                  <l>And prayers to prosper both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fabianus</hi> and <hi>Clara,</hi> I thus joyne your hands.</l>
                  <l>Heavens send you joy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Callidus,</hi> thou wert the instigator of my Anger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>So, all will out I see.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Who <hi>Callidus?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>What our friend?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Plainly I now perceive he cloathed his spight</l>
                  <l>Under pretence of duty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon I crave, J doe confesse J gave too great</l>
                  <l>A scope to envy and ambition, that a stranger</l>
                  <l>Should so much deserve your royall — And then</l>
                  <l>A hope to obtaine those honours should be took</l>
                  <l>From him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Gracious Soveraigne, I beg his punishment</l>
                  <l>May be refer'd to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Be it so.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I expect mercy; for you love —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>I did, before you prov'd false to the name</l>
                  <l>Of friend; but now resolve never to wed you:</l>
                  <l>And 'cause Ile not torment you to see another</l>
                  <l>Possesse my love, and for ever to keep my selfe</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17760:35"/>
                  <l>From solicitation, call forth a Priest of <hi>Vesta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>What will my dearest doe? <stage>Enter Priest.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus vow my selfe a Recluse.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                  <l>I am happy in so blest a Child.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>The mirrour of her Sexe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Then <hi>Callidus</hi> away, and learne to amend hereafter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Marania</hi> thou art cruell—Your Majesty hath</l>
                  <l>Shewne me mercy; I obey. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Now set forward toward <hi>Hymens</hi> Temple,</l>
                  <l>To confirme these Nuptialls; and</l>
                  <l>Let all stile it, that shall heare this story,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Noble Stranger,</hi> or eclipsed glory. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <l>OƲr Author knowing Fortitude's approv'd,</l>
            <l>When dangers threaten, if it stand unmov'd:</l>
            <l>He, without feare, freely presents his cause</l>
            <l>To you, for condemnation, or applause.</l>
            <l>Reserve severer doomes, for such as dare</l>
            <l>Boast their owne worth, he cannot feare or eare:</l>
            <l>Mistake him not, he vowes he is as cleare</l>
            <l>From bold presumption, as he is from feare.</l>
            <l>And if his <hi>Stranger</hi> has gain'd liking we' yee.</l>
            <l>Faith then shake hands, and bid him welcome te' yee.</l>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>